<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>rohitkumar, Author at PlainSwipe</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 15:48:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>How to Handle Out-of-Memory Errors when training LLMs</title>
		<link>./../../../how-to-handle-out-of-memory-errors-when-training-llms/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../how-to-handle-out-of-memory-errors-when-training-llms/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 15:46:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Introduction: As deep learning models continue to grow in complexity, the challenge of working with limited GPU RAM becomes increasingly prominent. Out-of-memory (OOM) errors can hinder the training process and limit the potential of your models. In this article, we explore a range of advanced strategies that go beyond the basics to prevent OOM errors&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../how-to-handle-out-of-memory-errors-when-training-llms/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">How to Handle Out-of-Memory Errors when training LLMs</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../how-to-handle-out-of-memory-errors-when-training-llms/index.html">How to Handle Out-of-Memory Errors when training LLMs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="wp-block-themeisle-blocks-advanced-heading-ffa67048" class="wp-block-themeisle-blocks-advanced-heading wp-block-themeisle-blocks-advanced-heading-ffa67048">LLamA v2, OpenLLamA, Falcon, etc.</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Introduction: </h3>



<p>As deep learning models continue to grow in complexity, the challenge of working with limited GPU RAM becomes increasingly prominent. Out-of-memory (OOM) errors can hinder the training process and limit the potential of your models. In this article, we explore a range of advanced strategies that go beyond the basics to prevent OOM errors and ensure efficient training within constrained GPU memory. We will discuss techniques like gradient accumulation, quantization, lit-GPT, automatic mixed-precision training, low-precision floats, efficient model initialization, choosing leaner optimizers, and parameter offloading.</p>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Gradient Accumulation</strong></h3>



<p>Gradient accumulation involves accumulating gradients over multiple mini-batches before performing a parameter update. This technique effectively reduces memory consumption during the backward pass since gradients from different mini-batches are stored and computed sequentially. By trading off computation time for memory, gradient accumulation can help prevent OOM errors. However, it&#8217;s important to adjust the learning rate accordingly, as fewer updates are being performed.Imagine you&#8217;re trying to paint a wall, but you can only hold a small amount of paint in your brush. Instead of painting the entire wall in one go, you paint a small section, then go back and paint another section, and so on. This way, you use up less paint at once, even though it takes a bit longer to finish the entire wall. Similarly, in training a model, gradient accumulation spreads out the updates so that the computer doesn&#8217;t get overwhelmed with too much information all at once.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Quantization</h3>



<p>Quantization is a method that reduces the precision of the weights and activations of a model, thereby saving memory. Floating-point numbers typically require more memory than fixed-point representations. Techniques like mixed-precision training utilize lower precision data types (such as float16) for activations and gradients while keeping higher precision for certain weights (like embedding layers). This helps in conserving GPU memory without significantly compromising model performance.Think of a recipe that calls for precise measurements of ingredients, like sugar. If you use a digital scale with many decimal places, you get very precise measurements, but sometimes you only need a rough estimate. So, you decide to use a simpler scale that rounds to the nearest gram. This is like quantization, where we simplify the numbers we use in the model to save memory, just like we&#8217;re using a simpler scale to measure ingredients.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Layer-wise Adaptive Rate Scaling (LoRA)</h3>



<p>Layer-wise Adaptive Rate Scaling is a technique designed to mitigate OOM errors during training. It involves adaptively adjusting the learning rates of individual layers based on their memory requirements. This allows memory-intensive layers to have smaller learning rates, preventing excessive memory usage. LoRA ensures that layers receive an appropriate amount of updates without causing memory overflow.Imagine you&#8217;re baking a layered cake, and each layer needs just the right amount of baking time to be perfectly moist. Layer-wise Adaptive Rate Scaling (LoRA) is like adjusting the oven temperature differently for each cake layer so that they all bake evenly. In a deep learning model, each layer learns at its own pace, and LoRA ensures that learning rates are customized, preventing some layers from overpowering others. This way, the model trains smoothly and produces accurate results, just like your cake layers come out delicious and balanced.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">&#8220;lit-GPT.&#8221; Lit-GPT (Lightweight Generative Pre-trained Transformer) </h3>



<p>is specifically designed to offer a balance between model size and performance. These models are often pre-trained on vast amounts of data, enabling them to capture essential patterns while maintaining a smaller number of parameters compared to their larger counterparts. Lit-GPT models are particularly advantageous when dealing with constrained GPU resources. Their reduced parameter count directly translates to lower memory consumption during training, making them less likely to encounter OOM errors. Despite their smaller size, they still exhibit impressive language generation capabilities, making them a valuable asset for various natural language processing tasks.By opting for lit-GPT models, you can effectively sidestep the challenges associated with limited GPU RAM. These models allow you to work with intricate language patterns and generate high-quality text while operating within the confines of your available memory resources. Imagine you have two storybooks—one is a giant encyclopedia, and the other is a smaller book that still tells you many interesting stories. The smaller book is like a lightweight model; it has fewer pages (parameters) but still captures the essence of the stories (language patterns). You can read and enjoy stories from the smaller book without feeling overwhelmed, just like you can use a lightweight model on your computer without running out of memory.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Automatic Mixed-Precision Training</h3>



<p>Automatic mixed-precision training combines both high and low-precision operations within a single training iteration. This technique optimizes memory usage by using lower precision for less critical operations, reducing memory footprint and accelerating training without compromising on model quality. Picture yourself working on a jigsaw puzzle. Some pieces have intricate details that you need to fit together precisely, while others are larger and less detailed. Instead of using a single-size tool for all the pieces, you switch between a fine-tipped tool for the detailed parts and a broader tool for the bigger parts. Similarly, in mixed-precision training, we use different &#8220;tools&#8221; (number representations) for different parts of the model to make the training process faster and more memory-efficient.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Low-Precision Floats</h3>



<p>Using low-precision floating-point representations, such as float16, for training and inference significantly reduces memory requirements. While some precision may be lost, the impact on model performance can be minimal, and the benefits in terms of memory conservation are substantial. Imagine you have a balance scale that measures weight. If you use a scale that measures weight very accurately, you&#8217;ll see very small changes even if you add just a tiny bit of weight. Now, think of using a scale that rounds to the nearest kilogram. You might not catch tiny changes, but it&#8217;s much faster and easier to use. Similarly, low-precision floats round numbers to make them simpler, which saves memory and speeds up calculations in the model.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Efficient Model Initialization</h3>



<p>Proper model initialization can influence convergence and memory efficiency. Techniques like &#8220;Xavier&#8221; initialization set initial weights in a way that promotes faster convergence, potentially requiring fewer training iterations and less memory consumption. Think of a car engine. When it&#8217;s cold, it takes a little while to start running smoothly. If you warm up the engine a bit before driving, it&#8217;s more efficient and uses less fuel. Similarly, in training a model, efficient initialization sets up the model in a way that helps it start learning more effectively and with less memory &#8220;wasted&#8221; on unnecessary steps.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Leaner Optimizers</h3>



<p>Choosing leaner optimization algorithms, such as AdamW or RMSprop, instead of heavier optimizers like vanilla Adam, can lead to reduced memory consumption. These algorithms often have memory-efficient implementations and provide good convergence properties. Consider two ways of carrying groceries: a backpack and a trolley. If you have fewer groceries, using a backpack is more efficient because it&#8217;s easier to carry around. Similarly, leaner optimizers are like using a backpack for your model—they&#8217;re lighter and more efficient, allowing the training process to run smoothly without needing too much &#8220;energy&#8221; (memory) to move forward.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Parameter Offloading</h3>



<p>Offloading certain parameters to the CPU during training can alleviate memory pressure on the GPU. By temporarily storing infrequently used parameters on the CPU, you free up GPU memory for more critical computations. Imagine you&#8217;re baking cookies, and you have a limited counter space. Some ingredients are used frequently, so you keep them on the counter. But other ingredients that you use less often, like a special spice, you keep in a nearby cupboard and only take them out when needed. Offloading parameters is like temporarily moving some ingredients off the counter to the cupboard, freeing up space for the important stuff and preventing clutter.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h2>



<p>Navigating the challenges of limited GPU RAM while training deep learning models requires a combination of strategies tailored to your specific needs. Employing techniques like gradient accumulation, quantization, lit-GPT, automatic mixed-precision training, low-precision floats, efficient model initialization, choosing leaner optimizers, and parameter offloading can collectively empower you to achieve efficient training and prevent out-of-memory errors. Experimentation and careful implementation of these advanced strategies will allow you to harness the full potential of your models within the confines of constrained GPU memory.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../how-to-handle-out-of-memory-errors-when-training-llms/index.html">How to Handle Out-of-Memory Errors when training LLMs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../how-to-handle-out-of-memory-errors-when-training-llms/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Optimal Nutritional and Pharmacological Approaches for Managing Type 2 Diabetes</title>
		<link>./../../../optimal-nutritional-and-pharmacological-approaches-for-managing-type-2-diabetes/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../optimal-nutritional-and-pharmacological-approaches-for-managing-type-2-diabetes/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 10:58:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=952</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>&#8230;and How AI can help Introduction I recently had the opportunity to attend the AACE Diabetes Conclave, where experts presented valuable insights into managing Type 2 Diabetes (T2D). Ralph A. DeFronzo, a renowned expert in the field of diabetes research, recently delivered an insightful talk at a conference, shedding light on the latest advancements in&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../optimal-nutritional-and-pharmacological-approaches-for-managing-type-2-diabetes/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Optimal Nutritional and Pharmacological Approaches for Managing Type 2 Diabetes</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../optimal-nutritional-and-pharmacological-approaches-for-managing-type-2-diabetes/index.html">Optimal Nutritional and Pharmacological Approaches for Managing Type 2 Diabetes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h1 class="wp-block-heading">&#8230;and How AI can help</h1>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Introduction</h2>



<p>I recently had the opportunity to attend the AACE Diabetes Conclave, where experts presented valuable insights into managing Type 2 Diabetes (T2D). <a href="http://www.uthscsa.edu/patient-care/physicians/providers/1851408843/Ralph-DeFronzo">Ralph A. DeFronzo</a>, </p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="318" height="318" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-3.png" alt="" class="wp-image-954" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-3.png 318w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-3-300x300.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-3-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 318px) 100vw, 318px" /></figure></div>


<p>a renowned expert in the field of diabetes research, recently delivered an insightful talk at a conference, shedding light on the latest advancements in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/type-2-diabetes/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20351199#:~:text=Treatment%20also%20includes%20diet%20and,height%20to%20estimate%20body%20fat.">Type 2 Diabetes (T2D) management.</a> The conference covered various aspects, including nutritional therapy, long-term weight maintenance, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3712370/">GLP-1 analogues</a>, and combination therapy. This article aims to distill the key takeaways from his talk, focusing on essential topics such as personalized treatment approaches, the role of GLP-1 receptor agonists, <a href="https://www.kidney.org/atoz/content/sglt2-inhibitors#:~:text=SGLT2%20inhibitors%2C%20which%20are%20also,leaves%20through%20in%20your%20urine.">SGLT2 inhibitors</a>, and the Defranzo algorithm for optimal glycemic control.I will share some key takeaways from the conference that can help individuals better understand and manage T2D effectively.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Nutritional Therapy for Type 2 Diabetes</h3>



<p>One of the central themes discussed at the conference was the importance of nutritional therapy in managing T2D. The focus was on personalized approaches tailored to each individual&#8217;s needs. Studies have shown that an individualized, reduced caloric intake (-500 to -700 cal/day) can be effective as long as the diet is maintained. The Mediterranean diet was highlighted as a beneficial option, involving reduced simple sugars, increased fiber/plant sterols, and mono- and polyunsaturated fats. Long-chain omega-3 fatty acids (EPA, DHA) were also noted to have proven benefits. Additionally, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/dash-diet/art-20048456">the DASH diet</a>, which is rich in potassium and low in sodium, and vegetarian or time-restricted diets were shown to be effective in managing T2D.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">How AI can assist?</h4>



<p>AI can assist in developing personalized and effective caloric intake plans for managing T2D.For example, when designing a Mediterranean diet plan, AI can take into account factors like reduced simple sugars, increased fiber/plant sterols, and mono- and polyunsaturated fats. AI can also identify appropriate sources of long-chain <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22332096/">omega-3 fatty acids (EPA, DHA)</a>, aligning with the proven benefits mentioned in the conference.AI can monitor food intake, analyze nutrient intake, and provide real-time feedback to the user. For example, if someone exceeds their recommended daily caloric intake, the AI chatbot can provide gentle reminders and suggestions for healthier food choices. AI can assist in creating meal plans and suggesting healthy recipes that align with specific dietary requirements, such as the DASH diet or vegetarian options.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Long-Term Maintenance of Weight Loss</h3>



<p>Maintaining weight loss over the long term is a significant challenge for individuals with T2D. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5764193/">A meta-analysis of 29 studies</a> and 4,146 participants revealed that after initial weight loss of 10.5 kg, an average of 7 kg was regained after four years, with a discouraging 71% weight regain after 4.5 years. These findings emphasize the need for sustainable lifestyle changes and continuous support to prevent weight regain and improve overall health outcomes.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">GLP-1 Analogs &#8211; A Promising Treatment Option:</h3>



<p> GLP-1 analogues, a class of medications, emerged as a promising treatment option for T2D. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK551568/">Drugs like Exenatide BID, Lixisenatide, Liraglutide, Exenatide QW, Albiglutide QW, Dulaglutide QW, Semaglutide QW</a>, and oral Semaglutide have shown efficacy in improving glycemic control and promoting weight loss. Semaglutide &#8211; oral, and Tirzepatide are among the newer formulations, offering alternatives for patients who may prefer non-injectable options.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Combination Therapy for Rapid and Effective Glycemic Control</h3>



<p>T2D is a progressive disease, and it becomes challenging to maintain glycemic targets with monotherapy over time. Traditionally, stepwise addition of medications to metformin has been recommended. However, recent data supports the use of initial combination therapy for achieving glycemic goals more rapidly and maintaining longer-lasting glycemic effects. This approach may offer better control of blood sugar levels, potentially reducing the risk of diabetes-related complications.</p>



<p>For patients using GLP-1 analogs or combination therapy, AI chatbots can serve as reliable medication reminders, helping patients adhere to their prescribed regimens. By analyzing medical histories, glycemic responses, and other health parameters, the chatbot can offer insights into optimal drug combinations, considering factors like GLP-1 analogs, SGLT2 inhibitors, or other medications.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Regular Exercise &#8211; A Key to Diabetes Management:</h3>



<p>Imagine your body as a car that needs to run smoothly. Regular exercise is like fueling your car with the right gas. Just as fuel powers your car&#8217;s engine, exercise powers your body, especially when dealing with diabetes. By engaging in at least 30 minutes of moderate exercise every day, you give your body the energy it needs to improve insulin sensitivity and lower blood sugar levels. It&#8217;s like a powerful engine tune-up that helps your body work more efficiently and keeps your blood sugar in check.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Time-Restricted Eating for Glycemic Control</h3>



<p>Think of your body&#8217;s digestion system as a factory that works best during specific hours. <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S016882272300044X#:~:text=Time%2Drestricted%20eating%20(TRE)%2C%20where%20energy%20is%20consumed,intake%20to%20improve%20metabolic%20health.">Time-restricted eating </a>is like setting the factory&#8217;s operating hours, allowing it to function more smoothly and efficiently. By limiting the time window for eating, your body has more time to process food, which can enhance insulin sensitivity and promote weight loss. It&#8217;s like optimizing the factory&#8217;s production schedule, leading to better management of blood sugar levels and overall health.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">How AI can help? </h4>



<p>Think of AI as a helpful timekeeper for your meals. It&#8217;s like having a smart clock that tells you the best hours to eat, making sure you get the most out of your food. AI can remind you when it&#8217;s time to eat and when it&#8217;s time to pause, giving your body a break to process food efficiently. Just like how a good schedule helps you stay organized, AI can assist in keeping your eating habits on track, potentially supporting better insulin sensitivity and weight management.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Mediterranean Diet &#8211; A Heart-Healthy Choice</h3>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-5-1024x683.png" alt="" class="wp-image-956" width="491" height="327" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-5-1024x683.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-5-300x200.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-5-768x512.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-5-1536x1024.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-5-2048x1365.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-5-930x620.png 930w" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 100vw, 491px" /></figure></div>


<p>Metaphor: Consider your body as a garden that needs the right nutrients to flourish. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/mediterranean-diet/art-20047801">The Mediterranean diet</a> is like planting a variety of colorful and nutritious fruits, vegetables, and grains in your garden. Just as diverse plants enrich the soil and attract beneficial insects, the Mediterranean diet enriches your body with essential nutrients and lowers cardiovascular risks. It&#8217;s like cultivating a heart-healthy garden that supports better glycemic control and overall well-being.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">How AI can help? </h4>



<p>AI can be your personal nutritionist, customizing a tasty menu that suits your tastes and keeps your heart happy. It&#8217;s like having a digital chef that suggests delicious recipes packed with nutritious ingredients. AI knows which foods are good for you, like colorful fruits, veggies, and healthy fats, and can create a meal plan that supports your diabetes management goals. Like a culinary genius, AI offers ideas that can help you enjoy food while improving glycemic control and reducing heart risks.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-6-1024x683.png" alt="" class="wp-image-957" width="512" height="341" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-6-1024x683.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-6-300x200.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-6-768x512.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-6-1536x1024.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-6-2048x1365.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-6-930x620.png 930w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Medication Options for T2D</h3>



<p>Treating diabetes is like assembling a superhero team to protect your body. Each medication option is like a superhero with unique powers to battle high blood sugar levels. Metformin is like a protector, reducing sugar production in the liver. Pioglitazone is like an enhancer, making your body&#8217;s insulin work better. Insulin is like a lifesaver, stepping in when other superheroes need extra help. <a href="https://cardiab.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12933-023-01798-4#:~:text=Both%20glucagon%2Dlike%20peptide%2D1,risk%20%5B3%2C%204%5D.">GLP-1 RA and SGLT2 inhibitors</a> are like double agents, helping your body release insulin and remove excess sugar, all while promoting weight loss. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK542331/">DPP-IV inhibitors </a>are like guards, preventing the destruction of helpful hormones. Together, these superheroes work as a team to keep your blood sugar in check and protect your health.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Glucose Monitoring and the Defranzo Algorithm</h3>



<p>Imagine managing diabetes as navigating a ship through rough waters. Regular glucose monitoring is like having a reliable compass, guiding you through the storm. By checking your blood sugar levels regularly, you get crucial information about how your body is doing. The Defranzo algorithm is like a skilled captain, making informed decisions based on the compass readings. Just as the captain adjusts the ship&#8217;s course to sail smoothly, the Defranzo algorithm helps your healthcare team make personalized treatment adjustments to achieve the best control of your blood sugar levels.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h2>



<p>The AACE Diabetes Conclave provided valuable insights into managing Type 2 Diabetes, highlighting the significance of personalized nutritional therapy, long-term weight maintenance, GLP-1 analogues, and combination therapy. With AI&#8217;s potential assistance, these approaches can be further optimized, leading to better glycemic control and improved overall health outcomes for individuals with T2D.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../optimal-nutritional-and-pharmacological-approaches-for-managing-type-2-diabetes/index.html">Optimal Nutritional and Pharmacological Approaches for Managing Type 2 Diabetes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../optimal-nutritional-and-pharmacological-approaches-for-managing-type-2-diabetes/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Generative AI can help improve demand forecasting for logistics</title>
		<link>./../../../how-generative-ai-can-help-improve-demand-forecasting-for-logistics/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../how-generative-ai-can-help-improve-demand-forecasting-for-logistics/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2023 14:05:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=947</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>AI-powered demand forecasting for accurate inventory planning and proactive decision-making inlogistics. Consider this: it takes an average of 6 months to manufacture a tire (tire design, raw material sourcing, mixing and extrusion, tire building, curing, quality assurance, and packaging) and during this time, the market can undergo significant changes. Without precise forecasting, businesses risk being&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../how-generative-ai-can-help-improve-demand-forecasting-for-logistics/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">How Generative AI can help improve demand forecasting for logistics</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../how-generative-ai-can-help-improve-demand-forecasting-for-logistics/index.html">How Generative AI can help improve demand forecasting for logistics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">AI-powered demand forecasting for accurate inventory planning and proactive decision-making in<br>logistics.</h3>



<p>Consider this: it takes an average of 6 months to manufacture a tire (tire design, raw material sourcing, mixing and extrusion, tire building, curing, quality assurance, and packaging) and during this time, the market can undergo significant changes. Without precise forecasting, businesses risk being unprepared for fluctuations in demand, leading to excess inventory or stock-outs.</p>



<p>I recently attended an event <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/company/cii-il">CII IL &#8216;Solution de Technology, Automation &amp; Robotics</a>&#8216; on 21 July 2023, Hotel The Lalit, New Delhi. Session Chairman <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/rishidiwan103">Mr Rishi Diwan</a> did a great job of picking great panelists. In a thought-provoking panel discussion, top industry leaders from the logistics sector gathered to shed light on the game-changing impact of automation. The distinguished panelists included <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/anil-syal-2b410b90">Mr. Anil Syal</a>, President of Safexpress Private Limited; <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/devang-mankodi-76bb979">Mr. Devang Mankodi</a>, Vice President &#8211; Shared Service at DP World; <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/manish-gupta-543a1212">Mr. Manish Kumar Gupta</a>, Head &#8211; Spare Parts Logistics, Honda Cars India Ltd; <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/rajeshgupta21">Mr. Rajesh Gupta</a>, Head-Supply Chain Management, JK Tyre &amp; Industries Limited; and <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/vikas-kalra-50509144">Mr. Vikas Kalra, </a>Head-Supply Chain Management, Hindware Home Innovation Limited.</p>



<p>The logistics industry is undergoing a profound transformation with the advent of automation. This revolutionary technology is redefining operations, fostering efficiency, and propelling growth. Embracing automation empowers logistics providers to streamline processes, boost productivity, and expand their business horizons. By harnessing the full potential of automation, these companies can attain operational excellence, unearth inventive solutions, and maintain a competitive edge in a constantly evolving market.</p>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Demand planning and forecasting is the weakest link in the chain</h4>



<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beer_distribution_game">The bear game</a> is a popular logistics training exercise where participants simulate managing the movement of goods in a supply chain. It demonstrates the importance of demand forecasting in logistics by highlighting how accurate predictions help participants anticipate and respond to fluctuations in demand, allowing them to optimize inventory levels and ensure efficient supply chain management in a dynamic environment.Each participant takes on the role of a different supply chain stakeholder, such as a manufacturer, distributor, or retailer. As the game progresses, participants face challenges like transportation delays, stockouts, or sudden changes in demand.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Traditional forecasting vs AI-powered forecasting</h4>



<p>While traditional statistical demand forecasting relies on historical data spanning 24 to 26 months, its limited scope and inability to capture real-time factors hinder its accuracy (60/75%). In contrast, AI-powered demand forecasting, leveraging real-time data and machine learning algorithms, can surpass traditional methods. By incorporating variables like GDP growth, market dynamics, weather conditions, and more, AI-driven models can achieve 95 to 98% accuracy, empowering businesses to make data-driven decisions and stay agile in the face of market changes.</p>



<p>Similar to how Google Maps dynamically updates its estimated arrival time based on real-time traffic conditions, AI-powered demand forecasting should continuously adapt to changing market dynamics.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">How generative AI can make forecasting for logistics more accurate</h4>



<p>Generative AI, specifically Language Models like Large Language Models (LLMs), holds great promise in revolutionizing demand forecasting. LLMs can analyze vast amounts of textual data from diverse sources, such as customer reviews, social media, news articles, and industry reports. By comprehensively understanding customer sentiments, market trends, and emerging events, LLMs provide valuable insights for demand forecasting models. </p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Scenario Analysis made possible by generative AI</h4>



<p>LLMs can generate hypothetical scenarios based on given conditions, helping businesses anticipate various demand outcomes. This <a href="https://www.planettogether.com/blog/the-importance-of-what-if-scenarios-in-production-planning">scenario analysis allows demand planners to explore &#8220;what-if&#8221; situations </a>and strategize effectively for different scenarios.</p>



<p>This is how it could work:</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant: (Responding) Sure, let&#8217;s get started. Please upload the historical sales data and any other relevant market information.</p>



<p>User: (Uploads data) Here is the data for the past 24 months, including sales figures, customer feedback, and economic indicators.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant: (After analysis) Customer sentiment has been positive over the past few months, with a notable increase in interest for our new product line.</p>



<p>User: That&#8217;s promising! What about upcoming market trends?</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant: Predicts a potential surge in demand for our products due to a major industry event scheduled next month. Additionally, the analysis indicates a potential slowdown in customer interest during the following quarter.</p>



<p>User: Interesting! Based on these insights, what&#8217;s the forecast for the next quarter?</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant: With the current positive trends and the anticipated industry event, the LLM forecasts a 15% increase in demand for the next quarter. However, it also suggests being cautious about the following quarter due to the potential slowdown.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">LLMs being used to intelligently collect insights for accurate forecasting</h4>



<p>LLM can engage with customer service representatives, product managers, and sales teams to extract valuable insights from their interactions with customers.</p>



<p>Customer Service Representative: Hi! Sure, I can help. We&#8217;ve been receiving a lot of inquiries about the new clothing line, especially about the availability of certain sizes and colors.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant (LLM): Thank you for sharing that. Are there any recurring patterns in customer inquiries that you&#8217;ve noticed?</p>



<p>Customer Service Representative: Yes, customers have been asking about the fabric composition and the environmental certifications of our eco-friendly products.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant (LLM): That&#8217;s insightful. Do customers frequently provide feedback about the shopping experience related to our sustainable fashion line?</p>



<p>Customer Service Representative: Yes, we often receive positive feedback about the quality and comfort of our eco-friendly clothing, and customers appreciate our efforts to promote sustainable fashion.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant (LLM): (Initiating chat with Sales Representative at GreenEco) Hello! I&#8217;m the LLM-powered demand forecasting assistant. I&#8217;m interested in learning more about sales trends and customer preferences related to our new eco-friendly clothing line.</p>



<p>Sales Representative: Hi! I&#8217;d be happy to help. The sales for our eco-friendly clothing line have been steadily increasing, especially for our organic cotton t-shirts and recycled polyester jackets.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant (LLM): That&#8217;s insightful. Can you identify any specific factors contributing to the increased demand for these products?</p>



<p>Sales Representative: Yes, customers are increasingly conscious of sustainable fashion choices, and they appreciate the versatility and style of our eco-friendly clothing.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant (LLM): Thank you for sharing that. Have there been any notable changes in customer preferences or market trends that you&#8217;ve observed?</p>



<p>Sales Representative: We&#8217;ve noticed a growing interest in earth-toned colors and minimalist designs, aligning with the current sustainable fashion trends.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant (LLM): Valuable information! Now, let&#8217;s integrate these insights into our demand forecasting process for the new eco-friendly clothing line.</p>



<p class="has-neve-link-hover-color-color has-text-color">AI Assistant (LLM): (Analyzing customer service and sales data) Based on the chat with customer service, there&#8217;s a growing interest in our new eco-friendly clothing line, particularly regarding size availability, fabric composition, and environmental certifications.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h4>



<p>From the conversation with the sales team, we can observe an increasing demand for our organic cotton t-shirts and recycled polyester jackets. Customers&#8217; conscious choices towards sustainable fashion, along with the appeal of earth-toned colors and minimalist designs, are driving this trend.</p>



<p>By integrating these insights into our demand forecasting model, we can anticipate continued growth in demand for our eco-friendly clothing line. We can focus on optimizing inventory for popular products like organic cotton t-shirts and recycled polyester jackets while considering customers&#8217; preferences for fabric composition and environmental sustainability.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../how-generative-ai-can-help-improve-demand-forecasting-for-logistics/index.html">How Generative AI can help improve demand forecasting for logistics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../how-generative-ai-can-help-improve-demand-forecasting-for-logistics/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</title>
		<link>./../../../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With a license that authorizes commercial use! BUT &#8230;. Its better than falcon 7b on most benchmarks, and its 2x better than falcon on QuAC (Question Answering in Context), and MMLU (Massive Multitask Language Understanding). Way to go Yann LeCun, can&#8217;t wait to instruct fine tune this with QLORA. But there is a lot of concerns about the&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html">This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">With a license that authorizes commercial use! BUT &#8230;.</h4>



<p>Its better than falcon 7b on most benchmarks, and its 2x better than falcon on QuAC (Question Answering in Context), and MMLU (Massive Multitask Language Understanding). Way to go <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ACoAAAADFk0BbiOeu2Wrer11SaPH_5m1GM8pG6Q">Yann LeCun</a>, can&#8217;t wait to instruct fine tune this with QLORA. But there is a lot of concerns about the licenses, is it really open for commercial use?</p>



<p>So I analyzed  <a href="https://github.com/facebookresearch/llama/blob/main/LICENSE">Llama 2&#8217;s Community License Agreement</a>, and here are the results:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Fine tuning:</h3>



<p>The Llama 2 Community License Agreement does not explicitly mention fine-tuning. <a href="https://github.com/ZrrSkywalker/LLaMA-Adapter">Fine-tuning</a> is a common practice in the field of natural language processing (NLP) where a pre-trained language model, like Llama 2, is further trained on a specific dataset or task to make it more specialized and accurate for that particular use case.</p>



<p>Since the agreement grants a license to use, reproduce, distribute, and create derivative works of the Llama Materials, it is reasonable to assume that fine-tuning is allowed as long as it falls within the scope of the granted license. In other words, if you fine-tune Llama 2 and create a derivative model for a specific task or dataset, you can use and distribute that fine-tuned model under the terms of the Llama 2 Community License Agreement.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Attribution Notice:</h3>



<p>When distributing the Llama Materials or derivative works, you must include an attribution notice stating that Llama 2 is licensed under the LLAMA 2 Community License by Meta Platforms, Inc. </p>



<p>Example: Company G uses Llama 2 to develop an AI-powered chat application. When releasing the application, they include the required <a href="https://www.lawinsider.com/dictionary/attribution-notices">attribution notice</a> within the application&#8217;s documentation.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Ownership of Derivative Works</h3>



<p>If you create derivative works and modifications of the Llama Materials, you will be the owner of those works.</p>



<p>Example: Individual F develops a new AI algorithm using Llama 2 as a foundation and can claim ownership of their new algorithm.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">License to Use and Modify</h3>



<p>The Agreement grants you a non-exclusive, worldwide, non-transferable, and royalty-free limited license to use, reproduce, distribute, copy, create derivative works of, and modify the Llama Materials. </p>



<p>Example: Company E can create an AI-powered language translation service using Llama 2 and offer it to their customers.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Compliance with Laws and Regulations</h3>



<p>Your use of Llama Materials must adhere to all applicable laws and regulations, including trade compliance laws and regulations.</p>



<p>Example: Company D, based in the United States, must ensure that their use of Llama 2 complies with export control laws and regulations when providing their AI services to clients in other countries.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Prohibited Improving Other Models</h3>



<p>You are not allowed to use the Llama Materials or any results obtained from them to improve any other large language model that is not Llama 2 or its derivatives. </p>



<p>Example: Company C cannot use the knowledge gained from Llama 2 to enhance the capabilities of their own proprietary language model or any other language model they use in their products.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Monthly Active Users Limit: </h3>



<p>If your product or service, along with its affiliates, reaches over 700 million monthly active users, you must request a separate license from Meta, and until you receive such license, you cannot exercise the rights granted under the Agreement. </p>



<p>Example: Social media platform X uses Llama 2 for their AI-powered content moderation system. Once the number of their monthly active users crosses 700 million, <a href="https://en-gb.facebook.com/business/help/4740325989340856">they must seek a separate license from Meta</a> to continue using Llama 2 in their system. This one I find less of a restriction for startup companies and most medium size use cases.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Redistribution to Third Parties: </h3>



<p>If you distribute or make the Llama Materials or any derivative works thereof available to a third party, you must provide a copy of the License Agreement to them. This means you cannot simply give the Llama Materials to others without informing them of the terms and conditions. </p>



<p>Example: Company A creates an AI-powered chatbot using Llama 2 and wants to sell it to Company B for use on their website. Before doing so, Company A must provide a copy of the License Agreement to Company B</p>



<p>Overall, its good news for startups. Of course <a href="./../../../managing-model-training-costs/index.html">fine tuning</a> this beast is another challenge. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html">This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Empowering Doctors</title>
		<link>./../../../empowering-doctors/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../empowering-doctors/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 16:47:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=834</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>AI Chatbots for Streamlined Medical Practice Imagine a world where doctors have more time to focus on their patients, where administrative tasks are automated, and where patient care is optimized. This is the future we are entering with AI chatbots. Today, we will showcase live demonstrations of these chatbots in action, illustrating how they act&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../empowering-doctors/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Empowering Doctors</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../empowering-doctors/index.html">Empowering Doctors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">AI Chatbots for Streamlined Medical Practice</h2>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<p>Imagine a world where doctors have more time to focus on their patients, where administrative tasks are automated, and where patient care is optimized. This is the future we are entering with AI chatbots. Today, we will showcase live demonstrations of these chatbots in action, illustrating how they act as virtual assistants and intelligently streamline medical processes.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 1: Streamlining Medical History Collection </h3>



<p>One of the challenges doctors face is the time-consuming process of collecting and documenting patient <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK534249/">medical histories</a>. AI chatbots can act as intelligent assistants, collecting patient history through natural language conversations. These chatbots analyze and summarize the information, <a href="https://medicine.yale.edu/news-article/concise-summaries-only-please/">providing doctors with concise patient summaries</a>, saving valuable time and enabling more efficient diagnoses.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 2: Simplifying Prescription Generation</h3>



<p><a href="https://medicalschoolhq.net/prescription-writing-101/">Prescription writing</a> is another area where AI chatbots excel. We have developed an AI program that allows doctors to effortlessly generate prescriptions through natural language conversations. The program takes care of formatting and even retrieves previous prescriptions for easy modification. This streamlines the process and ensures better continuity of care for patients.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 3: Enhancing Patient Follow-up and Compliance </h3>



<p>AI-powered <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29779264/">reminders and follow-ups</a> play a crucial role in improving patient compliance and engagement. Our AI chatbots automatically send personalized reminders to patients, ensuring they adhere to medication schedules and appointments. This automated system not only enhances patient compliance but also frees up valuable administrative time for doctors.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 4: Advantages and Future Possibilities</h3>



<p>By embracing AI chatbots, doctors can optimize their workflow, improve diagnostic capabilities through concise patient summaries, streamline prescription generation, enhance documentation with AI-generated letterheads and patient databases, and stay at the forefront of medical advancements. The future possibilities are vast, and we are just scratching the surface of what AI can do in healthcare.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h3>



<p>In conclusion, AI chatbots are transforming medical practice by empowering doctors with time-saving techniques, improved diagnostic capabilities, streamlined prescription generation, enhanced documentation, and automated reminders and follow-ups. These advancements not only increase doctors&#8217; efficiency but also elevate the quality of patient care. By embracing AI technologies, we can revolutionize medical practice, save time, reduce administrative burden, and ultimately enhance patient outcomes. Thank you for joining us on this enlightening journey into the future of empowered doctors in the age of AI.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../empowering-doctors/index.html">Empowering Doctors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../empowering-doctors/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Managing Model Training Costs</title>
		<link>./../../../managing-model-training-costs/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../managing-model-training-costs/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 17:49:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=818</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The research arm of SemiAnalysis has done surveys of many startups and enterprises and arrived at ~$1.5 per SXM A100 GPU per hour as a baseline cost for large clusters of 256 GPUs with NVLink and 1.6T networking. Some companies have better deals with AWS, Azure, Oracle Cloud, CoreWeave, etc., but this is a baseline.&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../managing-model-training-costs/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Managing Model Training Costs</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../managing-model-training-costs/index.html">Managing Model Training Costs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The <a href="https://www.semianalysis.com/p/the-ai-brick-wall-a-practical-limit">research arm of SemiAnalysis</a> has done surveys of many startups and enterprises and arrived at ~$1.5 per SXM A100 GPU per hour as a baseline cost for large clusters of 256 GPUs with NVLink and 1.6T networking. Some companies have better deals with AWS, Azure, Oracle Cloud, <a href="https://www.coreweave.com/">CoreWeave</a>, etc., but this is a baseline. For example, the list price at Azure is only $1.36 per hour, but signing up for the 2020 released A100 for three years is not something most want to do. On-premises will also be cheaper over multiple years if utilization rates are high, but that is very difficult for most enterprises and startups to commit to/achieve.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Affordable AI Training: MosaicML Claims GPT-3 Level Models at a Fraction of the Cost</h3>



<p><a href="https://www.mosaicml.com/">MosaicML</a>, a company in the AI field, claims they can train models that are as good as GPT-3 (which is a super impressive model) for less than $500,000! They can even train smaller models for about $2,500,000. That sounds like a lot, but in the AI world, it&#8217;s actually quite affordable.</p>



<p>According to some research, the baseline cost for a big cluster of 256 GPUs (that&#8217;s a lot!) with all the fancy networking stuff is around $1.5 per GPU per hour.</p>



<p>You know, training AI models is not just about having a powerful machine and pressing a button. There are many other things to consider that can be quite costly &#8211; the people involved, <a href="https://www.datacamp.com/blog/top-mlops-tools">ML Ops tools</a> (which help manage the whole process), gathering and preparing the data, dealing with failures and restoring the process, and even handling situations where we want the model to learn from just a few examples. All of these components can add up to be quite expensive.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Power of Smaller Models: Chinchilla Scaling Observations Redefine Cost-Effective AI Training</h3>



<p>Nowadays, many people are following something called the <a href="https://www.superdatascience.com/podcast/the-chinchilla-scaling-laws">Chinchilla scaling observations</a>. These observations tell us that it&#8217;s more cost-effective to train smaller models with more data rather than training the biggest and most advanced models. While there are some criticisms of these observations, the overall idea is that we can get good results without spending too much money by focusing on smaller models with lots of data.</p>



<p>Imagine we have a really big model with lots and lots of parameters. These parameters help the model learn and make smart decisions. Right now, we can train a model with about 1 trillion parameters, and it would cost around $300 million to do so. That&#8217;s a huge amount of money!</p>



<p>To train such a big model, we would need a lot of powerful machines called A100s. If we had 100,000 of these machines working together, it would take about three months to finish training the model. This is something that big tech companies like Meta, Microsoft, Amazon, and others can afford because they have lots of money to spend on these machines.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Scaling Limits: The Challenges of Training Mega-Models with Trillions of Parameters</h3>



<p>But what if we wanted to go even bigger? Let&#8217;s say we wanted to train a model with 10 trillion parameters. <a href="https://mpost.io/ai-model-training-costs-are-expected-to-rise-from-100-million-to-500-million-by-2030/">The training costs would go up to around $30 billion</a>! That&#8217;s an enormous amount of money, even for the big tech companies. We would need one million of those A100 machines working together, and it would take more than two years to complete the training. It&#8217;s a really long time!</p>



<p>What&#8217;s more, the amount of power needed for all those machines and the networking required would be like having a nuclear reactor generating electricity. It&#8217;s not something we can easily handle with our current technology.</p>



<p>So, training models with trillions and trillions of parameters is not practical right now. It would cost too much money and take too long. Plus, there are limitations in terms of how accurate these models can be and how well they can be compressed.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Affordable Alternatives: Training AI Models on a Budget</h3>



<p>For organizations that don&#8217;t have the financial resources to train large-scale AI models with billions or trillions of parameters, there are still options available. Here are a few recommendations:</p>



<ol>
<li>Start small: Instead of aiming for the largest and most complex models, begin with smaller models that have fewer parameters. While they may not have the same level of performance as the massive models, they can still provide useful insights and results.</li>



<li>Use pre-trained models: Many pre-trained models are available that have been trained by big tech companies or research institutions. These models have already undergone extensive training and can be fine-tuned or adapted to suit specific tasks or domains. By using pre-trained models, organizations can save on the cost of training from scratch.</li>



<li>Focus on data quality and preprocessing: Data plays a crucial role in training AI models. Ensuring high-quality data and investing in data preprocessing techniques can have a significant impact on model performance. By optimizing data collection, cleaning, and labeling processes, organizations can improve their models&#8217; accuracy and effectiveness.</li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Optimizing Large Language Models: Unleashing Task-Specific Efficiency with Parameter Selection and Pruning</h3>



<p>To determine which parameters of a large language model are most suitable for your specific task, you can follow a process called &#8220;parameter selection&#8221; or &#8220;parameter pruning.&#8221; Here&#8217;s a step-by-step guide on how to do it:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@shaistha24/how-to-choose-a-pre-trained-model-afd3dbd75b45">Pretrained Model Selection</a>: Start by selecting a large pretrained language model that aligns with your task. Models like GPT-3 or BERT are commonly used as a starting point due to their extensive pretraining on diverse datasets.</li>



<li>Task-Specific Dataset: Gather a dataset that is relevant to your specific task. This dataset should consist of labeled examples that represent the input-output pairs you want the model to learn.</li>



<li>Parameter Importance Calculation: Apply a method to calculate the importance or relevance of each parameter based on the extracted activations. One popular technique is &#8220;<a href="https://pml4dc.github.io/iclr2020/pdf/PML4DC2020_17.pdf">magnitude-based pruning</a>&#8221; which ranks parameters based on their absolute values.</li>



<li>Parameter Pruning: Set a threshold value to determine which parameters to keep and which ones to discard. Parameters with values below the threshold are considered less important and can be pruned (removed) from the model.</li>



<li>Fine-tuning: Once you have pruned the unnecessary parameters, you can fine-tune the remaining parameters using your task-specific dataset. During fine-tuning, only the remaining parameters are updated, while the pruned parameters stay fixed.</li>



<li>Evaluation and Iteration: Evaluate the performance of the fine-tuned model on your task-specific validation or test dataset. If the results are satisfactory, you can proceed with deploying the model. Otherwise, you may need to iterate the process by adjusting the pruning threshold or exploring different model architectures or hyperparameters.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h3>



<p>By starting with smaller models, leveraging pre-trained models, and focusing on data quality and preprocessing, organizations can make significant progress. In the end, it&#8217;s not always about having the biggest and most complex model, but rather finding the right balance between model size, data quality, and computational resources.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../managing-model-training-costs/index.html">Managing Model Training Costs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../managing-model-training-costs/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GPT-4 Secret Sauce</title>
		<link>./../../../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 17:07:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=815</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Unveiling the Secret Sauce: How Sparse Model Architecture is Revolutionizing AI Inference! The Scaling Challenge: Why Size Isn&#8217;t Everything Have you heard about these dense transformer model architectures that companies like OpenAI, Google, Meta, TII, MosaicML, and a bunch of others are using? They&#8217;re all the rage in the AI world. But let me tell&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">GPT-4 Secret Sauce</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html">GPT-4 Secret Sauce</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Unveiling the Secret Sauce: How Sparse Model Architecture is Revolutionizing AI Inference!</h3>



<p>The Scaling Challenge: Why Size Isn&#8217;t Everything</p>



<p>Have you heard about these dense transformer model architectures that companies like OpenAI, Google, Meta, TII, <a href="https://www.research-live.com/article/news/databricks-to-acquire-mosaicml/id/5113812">MosaicML</a>, and a bunch of others are using? They&#8217;re all the rage in the AI world. But let me tell ya, they&#8217;re not perfect when it comes to scaling this stuff up.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Inference: The Real Battle in AI Scaling</h3>



<p>Here&#8217;s the deal: the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=35288063">real challenge</a> with scaling AI isn&#8217;t just about making these models bigger and beefier. Nah, the real brick wall hits when it comes to inference. That&#8217;s the process of generating predictions or outputs from these massive models. And let me tell ya, it&#8217;s a computational nightmare.</p>



<p>Think about it like this: as these models get larger, the amount of computing power needed for each inference task skyrockets. It&#8217;s like trying to power a rocket ship with a lawnmower engine. Just ain&#8217;t gonna cut it, my friends.</p>



<p>So, what&#8217;s the solution? Well, the key is to<a href="https://omdia.tech.informa.com/OM020291/Decoupling-AI-training-and-inference-will-change-the-future-of-AI-silicon"> decouple the training compute from the inference compute</a>. We wanna separate the resources used for training these models from the ones needed to generate predictions. That way, we can use our computational firepower more efficiently. It&#8217;s all about optimizing the process, baby!</p>



<p>Have you ever wondered how computers can think and make smart decisions, like answering questions or recognizing pictures? Well, one way they do it is by using big models with lots of special parts called parameters.</p>



<p>Now, when these models get really big, they can become a bit too slow and need a lot of power to work properly. It&#8217;s like trying to run a marathon with a heavy backpack on. Not very efficient, right?</p>



<p>So, to make things faster and more efficient, scientists came up with something called &#8220;<a href="https://goodboychan.github.io/machine_learning/2020/09/07/01-Overview-of-Sparse-Modeling.html#:~:text=The%20definition%20of%20sparse%20is,of%20non%2Dzero%20valued%20elements.">sparse models.</a>&#8221; These models are like superheroes that know how to save energy and work smartly.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Here&#8217;s how it works</h3>



<p>Imagine you have a big group of superheroes, </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-824" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-1024x576.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-300x169.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-768x432.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-1536x864.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>but not all of them need to do something for every task. Some superheroes are really good at solving math problems, while others are great at recognizing animals. So, instead of using all the superheroes all the time, we only use the ones that are the best fit for the job.</p>



<p>In the same way, sparse models only activate or use the special parts (parameters) that are needed for a specific task. They don&#8217;t waste energy or time on things that aren&#8217;t necessary. It&#8217;s like having a special toolbox with just the right tools for the job, instead of carrying around a heavy toolbox with all the tools in the world.</p>



<p>By using sparse models, computers can work faster, use less power, and still do a great job at thinking and making smart decisions. It&#8217;s like having a super-smart robot assistant that knows exactly what it needs to do without wasting any energy.</p>



<p>And that&#8217;s where the concept of sparse model architecture comes into play. In a sparse model, <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/neural-networks-parameters-hyperparameters-and-optimization-strategies-3f0842fac0a5">not every parameter is activated during inference.</a> We don&#8217;t need &#8217;em all firing at once. Instead, we only activate the specific parameters that are relevant to the task at hand. It&#8217;s like tuning your engine to run on exactly the right fuel for the job. Efficiency, my friends!</p>



<p>So, next time you hear about sparse models, remember that they&#8217;re like superheroes that make computers faster and more efficient. Pretty cool, huh?</p>



<p>Now, I gotta say, sparse model architecture ain&#8217;t a one-size-fits-all kinda deal. It&#8217;s all about finding that sweet spot between inference efficiency and model performance. It&#8217;s a delicate balancing act, like walking a tightrope over a pool of hungry sharks. Okay, maybe not that dramatic, but you get my point.</p>



<p>Figuring out which parts of the sparse model to use for each task is like having a clever system that knows how to choose the right tool for the job.</p>



<p>You see, scientists and engineers train these models with lots and lots of examples. It&#8217;s like teaching the model to learn and get really good at different tasks. During this training process, the model learns which parts are good at what. It&#8217;s kind of like training a dog to fetch a ball or sit on command. The model learns which parts are best suited for different tasks, just like the dog learns different tricks.</p>



<p>Once the model has learned from all those examples, it becomes really smart at recognizing patterns. So, when it&#8217;s time to use the model for a specific task, it knows which parts to activate. It&#8217;s like the model&#8217;s brain says, &#8220;Hey, I&#8217;ve seen this kind of task before, and I know which parts are best for it!&#8221;</p>



<p>Think of it like a superhero team. Each superhero has their own special power, right? </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-825" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-1024x683.jpg 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-300x200.jpg 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-768x512.jpg 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-930x620.jpg 930w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>When a problem comes up, they know which superhero&#8217;s power is the most useful for solving it. It&#8217;s the same idea with the sparse model. It has different parts (like superheroes) that know which ones to use for different tasks.</p>



<p>By using all the knowledge it gained during training, the model can quickly figure out which parts to activate for each task it faces. It&#8217;s a bit like having a super-smart assistant who knows exactly which tools to use for different jobs.</p>



<p>So, the model becomes really good at choosing the right parts to use based on what it needs to do. It&#8217;s like having a brain that knows which buttons to press to make everything work just right.</p>



<p>By embracing sparse model architectures, these companies can overcome the challenges of scaling AI models for inference. They can separate the heavy training stuff from the nimble inference stuff, making their AI systems faster, more efficient, and ready to tackle real-world problems.</p>



<p>So, next time you hear about these dense transformer models, remember the real battle is in the realm of inference. And sparse model architecture is the secret weapon to make it all work. It&#8217;s like giving your AI system a turbo boost while sipping on a smooth whiskey.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html">GPT-4 Secret Sauce</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../gpt-4-secret-sauce/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GPT-4: Details Leaked</title>
		<link>./../../../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 16:49:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>GPT-4: A Closer Look at Parameters, Training, and Inference https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36674905 OpenAI&#8217;s latest language model, GPT-4, has been making waves in the AI community with its impressive size and capabilities. In this article, we will delve into the details of GPT-4&#8217;s parameters, training process, and inference architecture, shedding light on the advancements made by OpenAI. Parameter&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">GPT-4: Details Leaked</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html">GPT-4: Details Leaked</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>GPT-4: A Closer Look at Parameters, Training, and Inference</p>



<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36674905">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36674905</a></p>



<p>OpenAI&#8217;s latest language model, GPT-4, has been making waves in the AI community with its impressive size and capabilities. In this article, we will delve into the details of GPT-4&#8217;s parameters, training process, and inference architecture, shedding light on the advancements made by OpenAI.</p>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Parameter Count: Scaling Up Significantly</h3>



<p>GPT-4 boasts a remarkable size, with more than 10 times the number of parameters compared to its predecessor, GPT-3. It is estimated to have approximately 1.8 trillion parameters across 120 layers. This increase in parameter count signifies a substantial leap forward in model size and complexity.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Mixture of Experts (MoE): Cost-Effective Solution</h3>



<p>To manage the costs associated with such a massive model, OpenAI implemented a mixture of experts (MoE) model in GPT-4. This approach utilizes 16 experts, each consisting of around 111 billion parameters for the <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/multilayer-perceptron-explained-with-a-real-life-example-and-python-code-sentiment-analysis-cb408ee93141">MLP (Multi-Layer Perceptron)</a>. During each forward pass, two experts are routed, simplifying the routing process compared to more advanced algorithms discussed in the literature.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">MoE Routing: A Simpler Approach</h3>



<p>OpenAI&#8217;s routing algorithm for GPT-4 is reportedly straightforward compared to more intricate methods proposed in the research literature. The model employs approximately 55 billion shared parameters for attention, streamlining the routing process.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Inference Efficiency: Optimized Parameter Usage</h3>



<p>One notable aspect of GPT-4 is its impressive inference efficiency. Each forward pass for generating a single token utilizes only around 280 billion parameters and approximately 560 <a href="https://kb.iu.edu/d/apeq#:~:text=for%2031.69%20years.-,TeraFLOPS,every%20second%20for%2031%2C688.77%20years">TFLOPs (tera floating-point operations per second)</a>. This stands in stark contrast to the 1.8 trillion parameters and roughly 3,700 TFLOPs required for a purely dense model per forward pass. The optimized parameter usage contributes to improved performance and reduced computational requirements.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Dataset: Extensive Training Corpus</h3>



<p>GPT-4 is trained on a vast dataset comprising around 13 trillion tokens. It&#8217;s important to note that these tokens include both unique tokens and those generated during multiple epochs. The training process involves two epochs for text-based data and four epochs for code-based data. Additionally, OpenAI incorporated millions of rows of fine-tuning data from ScaleAI and internal sources to enhance the model&#8217;s performance.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">GPT-4 32K: Fine-Tuning the Context Length</h3>



<p>During the pre-training phase, GPT-4 uses an <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/understanding-context-length-hitch-gpt-models-arun-kesavan">8k context length (seqlen)</a>. However, the 32k seqlen version of GPT-4 is achieved through fine-tuning the 8k after the initial pre-training. This approach allows the model to handle longer sequences and capture more extensive context.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Batch Size: Striking a Balance</h3>



<p>OpenAI gradually ramped up the batch size over several days on the cluster, eventually reaching a batch size of 60 million. However, not every expert sees all tokens, resulting in an effective batch size of 7.5 million tokens per expert. The decision to limit the batch size ensures efficient processing and resource utilization.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Parallelism Strategies: Maximizing GPU Utilization</h3>



<p>To parallelize computations across multiple A100 GPUs, OpenAI implemented 8-way tensor parallelism, as this is the maximum supported by <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-in/data-center/nvlink/">NVLink</a>. Furthermore, they adopted 15-way pipeline parallelism to further optimize GPU utilization. It is speculated that OpenAI employed ZeRo Stage 1 and potentially utilized block-level <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2021/07/15/open-source/fsdp/">FSDP (Fully Sharded Data Parallelism) </a>for certain aspects of the training process.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Training Cost: An Expensive Endeavor</h3>



<p>The training of GPT-4 came with substantial costs. OpenAI&#8217;s training FLOPS (floating-point operations per second) for GPT-4 amounted to approximately 2.15e25, utilizing around 25,000 A100 GPUs for 90 to 100 days at a utilization rate of 32% to 36% <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/figure/The-MFU-Cache-Architecture_fig2_2396616">MFU (Memory Frequency Utilization)</a>. Due to numerous failures requiring restarts from checkpoints, the utilization rate remained low. Based on an estimated cloud cost of $1 per A100 hour, the training costs for this run alone would reach approximately $63 million. It is worth noting that pre-training with ~8,192 H100 GPUs could have been done in around 55 days for $21.5 million at a rate of $2 per H100 hour.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Mixture of Expert Tradeoffs: Finding the Right Balance</h3>



<p>OpenAI made specific tradeoffs in implementing the mixture of experts model. While research has shown that using 64 to 128 experts achieves better loss compared to 16 experts, OpenAI chose a more conservative approach. The decision to stick with 16 experts was driven by the challenges associated with generalization across multiple tasks and the difficulty in achieving convergence with a larger number of experts.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">GPT-4 Inference Cost: Scaling with Complexity</h3>



<p>The cost of GPT-4&#8217;s inference is approximately three times higher than that of the 175B parameter GPT-3 model (Davinci). This increased cost primarily stems from the larger clusters required for GPT-4 and the lower utilization achieved during inference. An estimated cost of $0.0049 cents per 1,000 tokens is anticipated for using 128 A100 GPUs to infer GPT-4 with an 8k seqlen. In comparison, the cost reduces to $0.0021 cents per 1,000 tokens when employing 128 H100 GPUs for the same inference task. It should be noted that these estimates assume high utilization and significant batch sizes.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Multi-Query Attention (MQA): Streamlining Processing</h3>



<p>Like many other models, GPT-4 utilizes <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13245">Multi-Query Attention (MQA)</a>. The introduction of MQA reduces the number of attention heads required, leading to a significant reduction in memory capacity for the Key-Value (KV) cache. However, due to the model&#8217;s size, the 32k seqlen GPT-4 cannot run on 40GB A100 GPUs, and the 8k seqlen version has limitations on maximum batch size.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Continuous Batching: Balancing Latency and Inference Costs</h3>



<p>OpenAI has implemented variable batch sizes and continuous batching in GPT-4&#8217;s inference process. This allows for some level of maximum latency while optimizing the overall inference costs. The combination of variable batch sizes and continuous batching ensures efficient resource utilization while maintaining a balance between response times and computational expenses.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Vision Multi-Modal: Enhancing Capabilities</h3>



<p>GPT-4 incorporates a separate vision encoder alongside the text encoder, featuring <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/method/cross-attention-module#:~:text=The%20Cross%2DAttention%20module%20is,are%20projections%20to%20align%20dimensions.">cross-attention</a>. The architecture is similar to Flamingo, adding additional parameters on top of the 1.8 trillion present in GPT-4. The vision model undergoes fine-tuning with an additional ~2 trillion tokens after the initial text-only pre-training. The primary purpose of this vision capability is to enable autonomous agents to read web pages, transcribe content from images and videos, and interact with multi-modal inputs.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Speculative Decoding: Enhancing Inference Efficiency</h3>



<p>There are indications that OpenAI may be employing speculative decoding during GPT-4&#8217;s inference process, although this is not confirmed. Speculative decoding involves using a smaller, faster model to generate several tokens in advance. These tokens are then fed into a larger oracle model as a single batch. If the small model&#8217;s predictions align with the larger model&#8217;s output, several tokens can be decoded in a batch. However, if the larger model rejects the tokens predicted by the smaller model, the rest of the batch is discarded, and the inference continues with the larger model. This approach can optimize efficiency but may impact the quality of generated sequences.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Inference Architecture: Distributed Computing Power</h3>



<p>GPT-4&#8217;s inference is carried out on a cluster comprising 128 GPUs. Multiple clusters are distributed across various data centers in different locations. The model utilizes 8-way tensor parallelism and 16-way pipeline parallelism to effectively leverage the available computational resources. Each node of 8 GPUs handles approximately 130 billion parameters, accommodating the model&#8217;s overall size. The design of the architecture allows for efficient parallel processing and scalability.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Dataset Mixture: A Diverse Training Corpus</h3>



<p>The training process for GPT-4 incorporates a mixture of datasets. The model is trained on approximately 13 trillion tokens, with CommonCrawl and RefinedWeb datasets contributing 5 trillion tokens each. Deduplicating tokens from multiple epochs yields a more reasonable estimate of the &#8220;unaccounted for&#8221; tokens, often referred to as the &#8220;secret&#8221; data. Speculations suggest that parts of this data come from sources such as Twitter, Reddit, YouTube, and platforms like LibGen, Sci-Hub, and GitHub.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">GPT-4&#8217;s Training and Knowledge: A Reflective Illusion</h3>



<p>GPT-4&#8217;s training on an extensive collection of college textbooks, coupled with its ability to answer questions from various domains, creates the illusion of intelligence. This illusion can make it appear knowledgeable in disciplines ranging from computer science to philosophy. Researchers have even attempted to extract memorized parts of books from GPT-4 to better understand its training data. Rumors suggest that the model possesses exceptional familiarity with unique IDs of Project Euler exercises.</p>



<p>In conclusion, GPT-4 represents a significant leap forward in terms of scale, capabilities, and training techniques. Its massive parameter count, mixture of experts model, and efficient inference architecture contribute to its enhanced performance. While the model&#8217;s training process involves a substantial investment, the use of diverse datasets and fine-tuning across multiple domains equips GPT-4 with a broad knowledge base. OpenAI&#8217;s approach to scaling language models demonstrates their commitment to pushing the boundaries of AI research and development.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html">GPT-4: Details Leaked</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../gpt-4-details-leaked/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Day Framework</title>
		<link>./../../../happy-day-framework/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../happy-day-framework/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:25:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mastering the HappyDay Framework: Unlocking Productivity and Happiness in Entrepreneurship Hey there, fellow entrepreneurs, hustlers, and go-getters! You know that feeling when you wake up in the morning, ready to take on the world, but then find yourself lost in a sea of tasks, decisions, and endless to-dos? Or that moment when you take a&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../happy-day-framework/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Happy Day Framework</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../happy-day-framework/index.html">Happy Day Framework</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h6 class="wp-block-heading">Mastering the HappyDay Framework: Unlocking Productivity and Happiness in Entrepreneurship</h6>



<p>Hey there, fellow entrepreneurs, hustlers, and go-getters! You know that feeling when you wake up in the morning, ready to take on the world, but then find yourself lost in a sea of tasks, decisions, and endless to-dos? Or that moment when you take a step back, analyze your day, and realize that you&#8217;ve been busy doing a million things, but somehow it feels like you&#8217;ve been running in circles. It&#8217;s a gut-wrenching feeling, isn&#8217;t it? </p>



<p>We pour our hearts and souls into our ventures, hustling day in and day out, only to discover that we might have been focusing on the wrong stuff. It&#8217;s frustrating, disheartening even. But here&#8217;s the truth: it happens to the best of us. We get caught up in the whirlwind of tasks and responsibilities, and lose sight of the bigger picture.</p>



<p>So how do we start our day without the chaos and decision fatigue and end our day feeling Happy?</p>



<p>I want to introduce you to the &#8220;HappyDay Framework&#8221; something i try to follow and has worked for me the days I am able to follow it.</p>



<p>HappyDay framework presents a comprehensive set of metrics that captures the key activities and outcomes necessary for success. By monitoring these metrics, startup founders can prioritize their daily tasks and evaluate their productivity. Let&#8217;s delve into the components of the HappyDay framework and understand how they help founders gauge their progress:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Metrics</th><th>Points</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Prospects added to list</td><td>1 point per 10 contacts added</td></tr><tr><td>Conversations with correct contacts</td><td>1 point per conversation</td></tr><tr><td>Value-based emails to Manager+ contacts</td><td>1 point per 5 emails sent</td></tr><tr><td>Initial meetings set</td><td>1 point per meeting</td></tr><tr><td>Opportunities created</td><td>1 point per opportunity</td></tr><tr><td>Personal development</td><td>1 point per hour of development</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Quest for Eight Points: Defining a Productive Day </h3>



<p>The HappyDay framework sets a target of eight points per day, representing a balanced approach that founders can adopt to ensure a productive day focused on sales activities. By aiming for eight points, founders allocate their time effectively across key areas, driving progress and nurturing customer relationships.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A daily checklist</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Main Activities</th><th>Second Level</th><th>Third Level</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Prospecting</td><td>Identify target market segments</td><td>&#8211; Analyze market research reports, industry trends, and customer surveys to identify potential segments.<br>&#8211; Evaluate the size, growth potential, and competitive landscape of each segment.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Utilize advanced search filters or tools on online platforms</td><td>&#8211; Utilize Boolean operators or advanced search options to refine search results.<br>&#8211; Leverage filters such as location, job titles, company size, or industry to target specific leads.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Analyze competitors&#8217; customer base</td><td>&#8211; Research competitors&#8217; websites, social media profiles, or case studies to identify their clients.<br>&#8211; Identify overlaps between competitor clients and your target market to find potential leads.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Keep track of prospecting activities using a CRM system</td><td>&#8211; Use a CRM tool to store and organize prospect information.<br>&#8211; Record interactions, notes, and follow-up tasks within the CRM for easy reference.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Regularly update and maintain the prospecting list</td><td>&#8211; Review and cleanse the prospecting list regularly to remove contacts that are no longer relevant.<br>&#8211; Follow up with unresponsive contacts or update their information if it has changed.</td></tr><tr><td>Conversations</td><td>Prepare a script or talking points</td><td>&#8211; Develop a framework that outlines key talking points, questions, and responses.<br>&#8211; Customize the script for different types of prospects or scenarios.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Practice active listening</td><td>&#8211; Engage in focused listening without interrupting or assuming.<br>&#8211; Ask clarifying questions to ensure a thorough understanding of the prospect&#8217;s challenges.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Take notes during conversations</td><td>&#8211; Use a note-taking tool or CRM system to document key points from each conversation.<br>&#8211; Capture actionable next steps, deadlines, or commitments made during the conversation.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Offer insights, case studies, or success stories</td><td>&#8211; Prepare a repository of relevant industry insights, case studies, or success stories.<br>&#8211; Tailor the examples or stories to resonate with the prospect&#8217;s specific pain points.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Build rapport and establish a relationship</td><td>&#8211; Find common interests or connections to establish a personal connection.<br>&#8211; Remember and reference previous conversations or details to show genuine interest.</td></tr><tr><td>Value-based emails to Manager+ contacts</td><td>Conduct thorough research on each Manager+ contact</td><td>&#8211; Review their LinkedIn profiles, company websites, or press releases for relevant information.<br>&#8211; Seek out news articles, interviews, or blog posts that provide insights into their challenges.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Customize each email</td><td>&#8211; Start with a personalized greeting that acknowledges their position or recent achievements.<br>&#8211; Reference their pain points or specific objectives to demonstrate understanding.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Incorporate relevant data, statistics, or industry trends</td><td>&#8211; Collect and compile data or statistics that highlight industry trends or challenges.<br>&#8211; Use credible sources and provide references or links to support the claims.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Craft compelling subject lines</td><td>&#8211; Use concise, attention-grabbing subject lines that convey value or urgency.<br>&#8211; A/B test subject lines to identify the most effective ones for different target audiences.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Follow up if there is no response</td><td>&#8211; Set up automated email sequences to follow up at strategic intervals.<br>&#8211; Consider alternative communication channels such as phone calls or LinkedIn messages for follow-ups.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h3>



<p>Startup journey is rewarding and extremely exhausting. It is a marathon and not a sprint. It is about consistency and patience, and doing things even when you don&#8217;t want to. The HappyDay framework I use is to bring structure to this chaos, reduce emotion from the game, and allow one to follow the startup life just like it is tasks that need to get done.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../happy-day-framework/index.html">Happy Day Framework</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../happy-day-framework/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</title>
		<link>./../../../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 19:16:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=805</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Harnessing the Power of Data Ownership Introduction Language models have revolutionized various aspects of artificial intelligence and natural language processing. With the advancements in technology and the availability of open-source models, many companies are considering the option of developing their own in-house Language Models (LLMs) by fine-tuning existing models on their proprietary data. This approach&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../../../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html">The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Harnessing the Power of Data Ownership</p>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Introduction</h3>



<p>Language models have revolutionized various aspects of artificial intelligence and natural language processing. With the advancements in technology and the availability of open-source models, many companies are considering the option of developing their own in-house Language Models (LLMs) by fine-tuning existing models on their proprietary data. This approach offers several advantages and challenges that need to be carefully considered. In this article, we will explore the reasons for and against implementing in-house LLMs and delve into the implications of data ownership in this context.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Enhancing Specialized Tasks:</h3>



<p>One of the primary advantages of fine-tuning an open-source LLM on proprietary data is the potential to improve performance on specialized tasks. A notable example is Microsoft&#8217;s in-house LLM, Turing NLG, which was trained on a diverse range of data, enabling it to generate human-like natural language responses across various applications. This demonstrates the value of in-house LLMs in enhancing specialized tasks that require domain-specific knowledge and industry expertise.</p>



<p>Here is a table that gives some use cases of why in-house LLMs are advantageous:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Use Case</th><th>Description</th><th>Why In-House LLM?</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Legal Research</td><td>Law firms can develop in-house LLMs to analyze and extract relevant information from legal documents, contracts, and case law, improving research efficiency and accuracy.</td><td>In-house LLMs offer greater control over data privacy and confidentiality, ensuring sensitive client information remains within the firm&#8217;s control. Fine-tuning on proprietary legal data enhances accuracy and domain-specific knowledge.</td></tr><tr><td>Financial Analysis</td><td>Financial institutions can leverage in-house LLMs to analyze market data, perform sentiment analysis on news articles, and generate personalized investment recommendations for clients.</td><td>In-house LLMs enable customization and adaptation to specific financial domain requirements, ensuring compliance with industry regulations and providing a competitive advantage through proprietary insights.</td></tr><tr><td>Medical Diagnosis</td><td>Healthcare organizations can develop in-house LLMs to analyze patient medical records, lab reports, and clinical notes, aiding in accurate diagnosis, treatment planning, and patient outcomes.</td><td>In-house LLMs offer the opportunity to train on institution-specific medical data, leading to improved accuracy and tailored insights. Compliance with data protection regulations and maintaining patient privacy can be ensured.</td></tr><tr><td>Customer Support</td><td>Companies with extensive customer support operations can build in-house LLMs to power chatbots or virtual assistants, providing personalized and efficient responses to customer inquiries.</td><td>In-house LLMs allow for better control over the customer support experience, enabling customization, and the ability to address specific industry nuances and jargon. Data privacy concerns can be mitigated, as sensitive customer information remains in-house.</td></tr><tr><td>Content Moderation</td><td>Social media platforms and online communities can develop in-house LLMs to automatically detect and moderate offensive or harmful content, ensuring a safer and more inclusive online environment.</td><td>In-house LLMs provide greater control over content moderation, allowing customization to specific community guidelines, cultural sensitivities, and evolving content trends. Data privacy and security are better maintained within the organization.</td></tr><tr><td>Language Translation</td><td>Organizations with a need for accurate and secure translation services can create in-house LLMs to translate documents, customer communications, and website content, ensuring confidentiality and control over sensitive data.</td><td>In-house LLMs offer the advantage of customization to specific translation requirements, including industry-specific terminology and internal jargon. Data privacy concerns are addressed by keeping translation processes in-house.</td></tr><tr><td>Fraud Detection</td><td>Financial institutions and e-commerce companies can utilize in-house LLMs to detect fraudulent activities by analyzing patterns, anomalies, and transactional data, enhancing security and minimizing losses.</td><td>In-house LLMs enable customization to specific fraud detection needs, incorporating proprietary knowledge and insights. Confidentiality of transactional and customer data can be better safeguarded.</td></tr><tr><td>Sentiment Analysis</td><td>Marketing and market research firms can develop in-house LLMs to analyze social media posts, customer reviews, and survey responses, providing insights into public sentiment towards products or brands.</td><td>In-house LLMs allow for customization to industry-specific sentiment analysis requirements, including specific product features, customer demographics, and sentiment nuances. Proprietary data and insights can be leveraged for a competitive advantage.</td></tr><tr><td>Compliance Monitoring</td><td>Companies operating in highly regulated industries can employ in-house LLMs to monitor and analyze vast amounts of data for compliance with regulatory requirements, reducing risks and ensuring adherence to guidelines.</td><td>In-house LLMs enable customization to specific regulatory frameworks, industry-specific compliance needs, and proprietary data sources. Better control over data privacy and security can be maintained.</td></tr><tr><td>Personalized Recommender Systems</td><td>E-commerce platforms and content streaming services can utilize in-house LLMs</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Data Ownership as a Deciding Factor:</h3>



<p>For many companies, the ownership of data is a critical consideration. Accessing proprietary data through third-party APIs may raise concerns regarding data privacy, security, and confidentiality. Companies like Apple have emphasized data privacy by developing Siri, their voice assistant, with an in-house LLM approach. This ensures that user data remains within the company&#8217;s control, addressing privacy concerns and providing a competitive advantage in the market.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Responsibility for Output and Safety:</h3>



<p>Regardless of whether a company relies on external APIs or in-house LLMs, it remains responsible for the outputs generated by its AI systems. Ethical considerations and potential harm caused by AI outputs are the responsibility of the company utilizing the technology. OpenAI&#8217;s GPT-3, a widely used language model, has shown instances of biased and harmful outputs, emphasizing the importance of thorough checks and balances. By building and fine-tuning their own LLMs, companies can exercise greater control and accountability over the system&#8217;s behavior, ensuring alignment with their desired standards of safety and ethical guidelines.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges and Considerations:</h3>



<p>While the benefits of in-house LLMs are evident, there are several challenges that companies must overcome. Firstly, the legal implications surrounding data usage must be carefully addressed. Different countries have varying &#8220;fair use&#8221; laws, and improper usage of proprietary third-party data can lead to potential lawsuits and legal consequences. For example, Google faced legal challenges in the past regarding the use of copyrighted content in its search results.</p>



<p>Additionally, developing and maintaining in-house LLMs requires a specialized skill set. According to a report by Indeed, the demand for AI-related job roles, including natural language processing experts, has grown by 119% in the past three years. Finding professionals with the necessary expertise in machine learning and deep learning can be a significant challenge for companies.</p>



<p>Furthermore, implementing in-house LLMs can give rise to internal obstacles within a company. These projects often involve complex decision-making processes, internal debates, and political considerations. The necessary approvals and coordination across different departments can cause delays and hinder progress.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Future of In-House LLMs:</h3>



<p>As LLMs continue to evolve and become safer and higher performing out of the box, the adoption of in-house models is expected to accelerate. OpenAI&#8217;s GPT-3, for example, has showcased impressive language generation capabilities. Companies will have more confidence in using these models and fine-tuning them to meet their specific needs. With advancements in cloud computing and the decreasing costs associated with it, hosting and maintaining in-house LLMs will likely become more affordable over time, making it a viable option for an increasing number of organizations.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion:</h3>



<p>The decision to develop and deploy in-house LLMs requires careful consideration of the advantages and challenges involved. Fine-tuning an LLM on proprietary data can lead to improved performance on specialized tasks and greater control over data ownership. However, legal implications, skill requirements, and internal obstacles should be carefully evaluated. As technology progresses, the future of in-house LLMs looks promising, providing companies with the means to harness the full potential of AI while maintaining control and responsibility over their AI systems.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html">The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
