<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>PlainSwipe -</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</title>
		<link>./../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With a license that authorizes commercial use! BUT &#8230;. Its better than falcon 7b on most benchmarks, and its 2x better than falcon on QuAC (Question Answering in Context), and MMLU (Massive Multitask Language Understanding). Way to go Yann LeCun, can&#8217;t wait to instruct fine tune this with QLORA. But there is a lot of concerns about the&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html">This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">With a license that authorizes commercial use! BUT &#8230;.</h4>



<p>Its better than falcon 7b on most benchmarks, and its 2x better than falcon on QuAC (Question Answering in Context), and MMLU (Massive Multitask Language Understanding). Way to go <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ACoAAAADFk0BbiOeu2Wrer11SaPH_5m1GM8pG6Q">Yann LeCun</a>, can&#8217;t wait to instruct fine tune this with QLORA. But there is a lot of concerns about the licenses, is it really open for commercial use?</p>



<p>So I analyzed  <a href="https://github.com/facebookresearch/llama/blob/main/LICENSE">Llama 2&#8217;s Community License Agreement</a>, and here are the results:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Fine tuning:</h3>



<p>The Llama 2 Community License Agreement does not explicitly mention fine-tuning. <a href="https://github.com/ZrrSkywalker/LLaMA-Adapter">Fine-tuning</a> is a common practice in the field of natural language processing (NLP) where a pre-trained language model, like Llama 2, is further trained on a specific dataset or task to make it more specialized and accurate for that particular use case.</p>



<p>Since the agreement grants a license to use, reproduce, distribute, and create derivative works of the Llama Materials, it is reasonable to assume that fine-tuning is allowed as long as it falls within the scope of the granted license. In other words, if you fine-tune Llama 2 and create a derivative model for a specific task or dataset, you can use and distribute that fine-tuned model under the terms of the Llama 2 Community License Agreement.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Attribution Notice:</h3>



<p>When distributing the Llama Materials or derivative works, you must include an attribution notice stating that Llama 2 is licensed under the LLAMA 2 Community License by Meta Platforms, Inc. </p>



<p>Example: Company G uses Llama 2 to develop an AI-powered chat application. When releasing the application, they include the required <a href="https://www.lawinsider.com/dictionary/attribution-notices">attribution notice</a> within the application&#8217;s documentation.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Ownership of Derivative Works</h3>



<p>If you create derivative works and modifications of the Llama Materials, you will be the owner of those works.</p>



<p>Example: Individual F develops a new AI algorithm using Llama 2 as a foundation and can claim ownership of their new algorithm.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">License to Use and Modify</h3>



<p>The Agreement grants you a non-exclusive, worldwide, non-transferable, and royalty-free limited license to use, reproduce, distribute, copy, create derivative works of, and modify the Llama Materials. </p>



<p>Example: Company E can create an AI-powered language translation service using Llama 2 and offer it to their customers.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Compliance with Laws and Regulations</h3>



<p>Your use of Llama Materials must adhere to all applicable laws and regulations, including trade compliance laws and regulations.</p>



<p>Example: Company D, based in the United States, must ensure that their use of Llama 2 complies with export control laws and regulations when providing their AI services to clients in other countries.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Prohibited Improving Other Models</h3>



<p>You are not allowed to use the Llama Materials or any results obtained from them to improve any other large language model that is not Llama 2 or its derivatives. </p>



<p>Example: Company C cannot use the knowledge gained from Llama 2 to enhance the capabilities of their own proprietary language model or any other language model they use in their products.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Monthly Active Users Limit: </h3>



<p>If your product or service, along with its affiliates, reaches over 700 million monthly active users, you must request a separate license from Meta, and until you receive such license, you cannot exercise the rights granted under the Agreement. </p>



<p>Example: Social media platform X uses Llama 2 for their AI-powered content moderation system. Once the number of their monthly active users crosses 700 million, <a href="https://en-gb.facebook.com/business/help/4740325989340856">they must seek a separate license from Meta</a> to continue using Llama 2 in their system. This one I find less of a restriction for startup companies and most medium size use cases.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Redistribution to Third Parties: </h3>



<p>If you distribute or make the Llama Materials or any derivative works thereof available to a third party, you must provide a copy of the License Agreement to them. This means you cannot simply give the Llama Materials to others without informing them of the terms and conditions. </p>



<p>Example: Company A creates an AI-powered chatbot using Llama 2 and wants to sell it to Company B for use on their website. Before doing so, Company A must provide a copy of the License Agreement to Company B</p>



<p>Overall, its good news for startups. Of course <a href="./../managing-model-training-costs/index.html">fine tuning</a> this beast is another challenge. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/index.html">This is huge! Llama-v2 is open source</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../this-is-huge-llama-v2-is-open-source/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Empowering Doctors</title>
		<link>./../empowering-doctors/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../empowering-doctors/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 16:47:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=834</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>AI Chatbots for Streamlined Medical Practice Imagine a world where doctors have more time to focus on their patients, where administrative tasks are automated, and where patient care is optimized. This is the future we are entering with AI chatbots. Today, we will showcase live demonstrations of these chatbots in action, illustrating how they act&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../empowering-doctors/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Empowering Doctors</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../empowering-doctors/index.html">Empowering Doctors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">AI Chatbots for Streamlined Medical Practice</h2>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<p>Imagine a world where doctors have more time to focus on their patients, where administrative tasks are automated, and where patient care is optimized. This is the future we are entering with AI chatbots. Today, we will showcase live demonstrations of these chatbots in action, illustrating how they act as virtual assistants and intelligently streamline medical processes.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 1: Streamlining Medical History Collection </h3>



<p>One of the challenges doctors face is the time-consuming process of collecting and documenting patient <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK534249/">medical histories</a>. AI chatbots can act as intelligent assistants, collecting patient history through natural language conversations. These chatbots analyze and summarize the information, <a href="https://medicine.yale.edu/news-article/concise-summaries-only-please/">providing doctors with concise patient summaries</a>, saving valuable time and enabling more efficient diagnoses.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 2: Simplifying Prescription Generation</h3>



<p><a href="https://medicalschoolhq.net/prescription-writing-101/">Prescription writing</a> is another area where AI chatbots excel. We have developed an AI program that allows doctors to effortlessly generate prescriptions through natural language conversations. The program takes care of formatting and even retrieves previous prescriptions for easy modification. This streamlines the process and ensures better continuity of care for patients.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 3: Enhancing Patient Follow-up and Compliance </h3>



<p>AI-powered <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29779264/">reminders and follow-ups</a> play a crucial role in improving patient compliance and engagement. Our AI chatbots automatically send personalized reminders to patients, ensuring they adhere to medication schedules and appointments. This automated system not only enhances patient compliance but also frees up valuable administrative time for doctors.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Section 4: Advantages and Future Possibilities</h3>



<p>By embracing AI chatbots, doctors can optimize their workflow, improve diagnostic capabilities through concise patient summaries, streamline prescription generation, enhance documentation with AI-generated letterheads and patient databases, and stay at the forefront of medical advancements. The future possibilities are vast, and we are just scratching the surface of what AI can do in healthcare.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h3>



<p>In conclusion, AI chatbots are transforming medical practice by empowering doctors with time-saving techniques, improved diagnostic capabilities, streamlined prescription generation, enhanced documentation, and automated reminders and follow-ups. These advancements not only increase doctors&#8217; efficiency but also elevate the quality of patient care. By embracing AI technologies, we can revolutionize medical practice, save time, reduce administrative burden, and ultimately enhance patient outcomes. Thank you for joining us on this enlightening journey into the future of empowered doctors in the age of AI.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../empowering-doctors/index.html">Empowering Doctors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../empowering-doctors/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Managing Model Training Costs</title>
		<link>./../managing-model-training-costs/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../managing-model-training-costs/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 17:49:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=818</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The research arm of SemiAnalysis has done surveys of many startups and enterprises and arrived at ~$1.5 per SXM A100 GPU per hour as a baseline cost for large clusters of 256 GPUs with NVLink and 1.6T networking. Some companies have better deals with AWS, Azure, Oracle Cloud, CoreWeave, etc., but this is a baseline.&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../managing-model-training-costs/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Managing Model Training Costs</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../managing-model-training-costs/index.html">Managing Model Training Costs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The <a href="https://www.semianalysis.com/p/the-ai-brick-wall-a-practical-limit">research arm of SemiAnalysis</a> has done surveys of many startups and enterprises and arrived at ~$1.5 per SXM A100 GPU per hour as a baseline cost for large clusters of 256 GPUs with NVLink and 1.6T networking. Some companies have better deals with AWS, Azure, Oracle Cloud, <a href="https://www.coreweave.com/">CoreWeave</a>, etc., but this is a baseline. For example, the list price at Azure is only $1.36 per hour, but signing up for the 2020 released A100 for three years is not something most want to do. On-premises will also be cheaper over multiple years if utilization rates are high, but that is very difficult for most enterprises and startups to commit to/achieve.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Affordable AI Training: MosaicML Claims GPT-3 Level Models at a Fraction of the Cost</h3>



<p><a href="https://www.mosaicml.com/">MosaicML</a>, a company in the AI field, claims they can train models that are as good as GPT-3 (which is a super impressive model) for less than $500,000! They can even train smaller models for about $2,500,000. That sounds like a lot, but in the AI world, it&#8217;s actually quite affordable.</p>



<p>According to some research, the baseline cost for a big cluster of 256 GPUs (that&#8217;s a lot!) with all the fancy networking stuff is around $1.5 per GPU per hour.</p>



<p>You know, training AI models is not just about having a powerful machine and pressing a button. There are many other things to consider that can be quite costly &#8211; the people involved, <a href="https://www.datacamp.com/blog/top-mlops-tools">ML Ops tools</a> (which help manage the whole process), gathering and preparing the data, dealing with failures and restoring the process, and even handling situations where we want the model to learn from just a few examples. All of these components can add up to be quite expensive.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Power of Smaller Models: Chinchilla Scaling Observations Redefine Cost-Effective AI Training</h3>



<p>Nowadays, many people are following something called the <a href="https://www.superdatascience.com/podcast/the-chinchilla-scaling-laws">Chinchilla scaling observations</a>. These observations tell us that it&#8217;s more cost-effective to train smaller models with more data rather than training the biggest and most advanced models. While there are some criticisms of these observations, the overall idea is that we can get good results without spending too much money by focusing on smaller models with lots of data.</p>



<p>Imagine we have a really big model with lots and lots of parameters. These parameters help the model learn and make smart decisions. Right now, we can train a model with about 1 trillion parameters, and it would cost around $300 million to do so. That&#8217;s a huge amount of money!</p>



<p>To train such a big model, we would need a lot of powerful machines called A100s. If we had 100,000 of these machines working together, it would take about three months to finish training the model. This is something that big tech companies like Meta, Microsoft, Amazon, and others can afford because they have lots of money to spend on these machines.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Scaling Limits: The Challenges of Training Mega-Models with Trillions of Parameters</h3>



<p>But what if we wanted to go even bigger? Let&#8217;s say we wanted to train a model with 10 trillion parameters. <a href="https://mpost.io/ai-model-training-costs-are-expected-to-rise-from-100-million-to-500-million-by-2030/">The training costs would go up to around $30 billion</a>! That&#8217;s an enormous amount of money, even for the big tech companies. We would need one million of those A100 machines working together, and it would take more than two years to complete the training. It&#8217;s a really long time!</p>



<p>What&#8217;s more, the amount of power needed for all those machines and the networking required would be like having a nuclear reactor generating electricity. It&#8217;s not something we can easily handle with our current technology.</p>



<p>So, training models with trillions and trillions of parameters is not practical right now. It would cost too much money and take too long. Plus, there are limitations in terms of how accurate these models can be and how well they can be compressed.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Affordable Alternatives: Training AI Models on a Budget</h3>



<p>For organizations that don&#8217;t have the financial resources to train large-scale AI models with billions or trillions of parameters, there are still options available. Here are a few recommendations:</p>



<ol>
<li>Start small: Instead of aiming for the largest and most complex models, begin with smaller models that have fewer parameters. While they may not have the same level of performance as the massive models, they can still provide useful insights and results.</li>



<li>Use pre-trained models: Many pre-trained models are available that have been trained by big tech companies or research institutions. These models have already undergone extensive training and can be fine-tuned or adapted to suit specific tasks or domains. By using pre-trained models, organizations can save on the cost of training from scratch.</li>



<li>Focus on data quality and preprocessing: Data plays a crucial role in training AI models. Ensuring high-quality data and investing in data preprocessing techniques can have a significant impact on model performance. By optimizing data collection, cleaning, and labeling processes, organizations can improve their models&#8217; accuracy and effectiveness.</li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Optimizing Large Language Models: Unleashing Task-Specific Efficiency with Parameter Selection and Pruning</h3>



<p>To determine which parameters of a large language model are most suitable for your specific task, you can follow a process called &#8220;parameter selection&#8221; or &#8220;parameter pruning.&#8221; Here&#8217;s a step-by-step guide on how to do it:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@shaistha24/how-to-choose-a-pre-trained-model-afd3dbd75b45">Pretrained Model Selection</a>: Start by selecting a large pretrained language model that aligns with your task. Models like GPT-3 or BERT are commonly used as a starting point due to their extensive pretraining on diverse datasets.</li>



<li>Task-Specific Dataset: Gather a dataset that is relevant to your specific task. This dataset should consist of labeled examples that represent the input-output pairs you want the model to learn.</li>



<li>Parameter Importance Calculation: Apply a method to calculate the importance or relevance of each parameter based on the extracted activations. One popular technique is &#8220;<a href="https://pml4dc.github.io/iclr2020/pdf/PML4DC2020_17.pdf">magnitude-based pruning</a>&#8221; which ranks parameters based on their absolute values.</li>



<li>Parameter Pruning: Set a threshold value to determine which parameters to keep and which ones to discard. Parameters with values below the threshold are considered less important and can be pruned (removed) from the model.</li>



<li>Fine-tuning: Once you have pruned the unnecessary parameters, you can fine-tune the remaining parameters using your task-specific dataset. During fine-tuning, only the remaining parameters are updated, while the pruned parameters stay fixed.</li>



<li>Evaluation and Iteration: Evaluate the performance of the fine-tuned model on your task-specific validation or test dataset. If the results are satisfactory, you can proceed with deploying the model. Otherwise, you may need to iterate the process by adjusting the pruning threshold or exploring different model architectures or hyperparameters.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h3>



<p>By starting with smaller models, leveraging pre-trained models, and focusing on data quality and preprocessing, organizations can make significant progress. In the end, it&#8217;s not always about having the biggest and most complex model, but rather finding the right balance between model size, data quality, and computational resources.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../managing-model-training-costs/index.html">Managing Model Training Costs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../managing-model-training-costs/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GPT-4 Secret Sauce</title>
		<link>./../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 17:07:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=815</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Unveiling the Secret Sauce: How Sparse Model Architecture is Revolutionizing AI Inference! The Scaling Challenge: Why Size Isn&#8217;t Everything Have you heard about these dense transformer model architectures that companies like OpenAI, Google, Meta, TII, MosaicML, and a bunch of others are using? They&#8217;re all the rage in the AI world. But let me tell&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">GPT-4 Secret Sauce</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html">GPT-4 Secret Sauce</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Unveiling the Secret Sauce: How Sparse Model Architecture is Revolutionizing AI Inference!</h3>



<p>The Scaling Challenge: Why Size Isn&#8217;t Everything</p>



<p>Have you heard about these dense transformer model architectures that companies like OpenAI, Google, Meta, TII, <a href="https://www.research-live.com/article/news/databricks-to-acquire-mosaicml/id/5113812">MosaicML</a>, and a bunch of others are using? They&#8217;re all the rage in the AI world. But let me tell ya, they&#8217;re not perfect when it comes to scaling this stuff up.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Inference: The Real Battle in AI Scaling</h3>



<p>Here&#8217;s the deal: the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=35288063">real challenge</a> with scaling AI isn&#8217;t just about making these models bigger and beefier. Nah, the real brick wall hits when it comes to inference. That&#8217;s the process of generating predictions or outputs from these massive models. And let me tell ya, it&#8217;s a computational nightmare.</p>



<p>Think about it like this: as these models get larger, the amount of computing power needed for each inference task skyrockets. It&#8217;s like trying to power a rocket ship with a lawnmower engine. Just ain&#8217;t gonna cut it, my friends.</p>



<p>So, what&#8217;s the solution? Well, the key is to<a href="https://omdia.tech.informa.com/OM020291/Decoupling-AI-training-and-inference-will-change-the-future-of-AI-silicon"> decouple the training compute from the inference compute</a>. We wanna separate the resources used for training these models from the ones needed to generate predictions. That way, we can use our computational firepower more efficiently. It&#8217;s all about optimizing the process, baby!</p>



<p>Have you ever wondered how computers can think and make smart decisions, like answering questions or recognizing pictures? Well, one way they do it is by using big models with lots of special parts called parameters.</p>



<p>Now, when these models get really big, they can become a bit too slow and need a lot of power to work properly. It&#8217;s like trying to run a marathon with a heavy backpack on. Not very efficient, right?</p>



<p>So, to make things faster and more efficient, scientists came up with something called &#8220;<a href="https://goodboychan.github.io/machine_learning/2020/09/07/01-Overview-of-Sparse-Modeling.html#:~:text=The%20definition%20of%20sparse%20is,of%20non%2Dzero%20valued%20elements.">sparse models.</a>&#8221; These models are like superheroes that know how to save energy and work smartly.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Here&#8217;s how it works</h3>



<p>Imagine you have a big group of superheroes, </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-824" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-1024x576.png 1024w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-300x169.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-768x432.png 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image-1536x864.png 1536w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/image.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>but not all of them need to do something for every task. Some superheroes are really good at solving math problems, while others are great at recognizing animals. So, instead of using all the superheroes all the time, we only use the ones that are the best fit for the job.</p>



<p>In the same way, sparse models only activate or use the special parts (parameters) that are needed for a specific task. They don&#8217;t waste energy or time on things that aren&#8217;t necessary. It&#8217;s like having a special toolbox with just the right tools for the job, instead of carrying around a heavy toolbox with all the tools in the world.</p>



<p>By using sparse models, computers can work faster, use less power, and still do a great job at thinking and making smart decisions. It&#8217;s like having a super-smart robot assistant that knows exactly what it needs to do without wasting any energy.</p>



<p>And that&#8217;s where the concept of sparse model architecture comes into play. In a sparse model, <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/neural-networks-parameters-hyperparameters-and-optimization-strategies-3f0842fac0a5">not every parameter is activated during inference.</a> We don&#8217;t need &#8217;em all firing at once. Instead, we only activate the specific parameters that are relevant to the task at hand. It&#8217;s like tuning your engine to run on exactly the right fuel for the job. Efficiency, my friends!</p>



<p>So, next time you hear about sparse models, remember that they&#8217;re like superheroes that make computers faster and more efficient. Pretty cool, huh?</p>



<p>Now, I gotta say, sparse model architecture ain&#8217;t a one-size-fits-all kinda deal. It&#8217;s all about finding that sweet spot between inference efficiency and model performance. It&#8217;s a delicate balancing act, like walking a tightrope over a pool of hungry sharks. Okay, maybe not that dramatic, but you get my point.</p>



<p>Figuring out which parts of the sparse model to use for each task is like having a clever system that knows how to choose the right tool for the job.</p>



<p>You see, scientists and engineers train these models with lots and lots of examples. It&#8217;s like teaching the model to learn and get really good at different tasks. During this training process, the model learns which parts are good at what. It&#8217;s kind of like training a dog to fetch a ball or sit on command. The model learns which parts are best suited for different tasks, just like the dog learns different tricks.</p>



<p>Once the model has learned from all those examples, it becomes really smart at recognizing patterns. So, when it&#8217;s time to use the model for a specific task, it knows which parts to activate. It&#8217;s like the model&#8217;s brain says, &#8220;Hey, I&#8217;ve seen this kind of task before, and I know which parts are best for it!&#8221;</p>



<p>Think of it like a superhero team. Each superhero has their own special power, right? </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-825" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-1024x683.jpg 1024w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-300x200.jpg 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-768x512.jpg 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/07/pexels-erik-mclean-7809123-930x620.jpg 930w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>When a problem comes up, they know which superhero&#8217;s power is the most useful for solving it. It&#8217;s the same idea with the sparse model. It has different parts (like superheroes) that know which ones to use for different tasks.</p>



<p>By using all the knowledge it gained during training, the model can quickly figure out which parts to activate for each task it faces. It&#8217;s a bit like having a super-smart assistant who knows exactly which tools to use for different jobs.</p>



<p>So, the model becomes really good at choosing the right parts to use based on what it needs to do. It&#8217;s like having a brain that knows which buttons to press to make everything work just right.</p>



<p>By embracing sparse model architectures, these companies can overcome the challenges of scaling AI models for inference. They can separate the heavy training stuff from the nimble inference stuff, making their AI systems faster, more efficient, and ready to tackle real-world problems.</p>



<p>So, next time you hear about these dense transformer models, remember the real battle is in the realm of inference. And sparse model architecture is the secret weapon to make it all work. It&#8217;s like giving your AI system a turbo boost while sipping on a smooth whiskey.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../gpt-4-secret-sauce/index.html">GPT-4 Secret Sauce</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../gpt-4-secret-sauce/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GPT-4: Details Leaked</title>
		<link>./../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 16:49:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>GPT-4: A Closer Look at Parameters, Training, and Inference https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36674905 OpenAI&#8217;s latest language model, GPT-4, has been making waves in the AI community with its impressive size and capabilities. In this article, we will delve into the details of GPT-4&#8217;s parameters, training process, and inference architecture, shedding light on the advancements made by OpenAI. Parameter&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">GPT-4: Details Leaked</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html">GPT-4: Details Leaked</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>GPT-4: A Closer Look at Parameters, Training, and Inference</p>



<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36674905">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36674905</a></p>



<p>OpenAI&#8217;s latest language model, GPT-4, has been making waves in the AI community with its impressive size and capabilities. In this article, we will delve into the details of GPT-4&#8217;s parameters, training process, and inference architecture, shedding light on the advancements made by OpenAI.</p>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Parameter Count: Scaling Up Significantly</h3>



<p>GPT-4 boasts a remarkable size, with more than 10 times the number of parameters compared to its predecessor, GPT-3. It is estimated to have approximately 1.8 trillion parameters across 120 layers. This increase in parameter count signifies a substantial leap forward in model size and complexity.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Mixture of Experts (MoE): Cost-Effective Solution</h3>



<p>To manage the costs associated with such a massive model, OpenAI implemented a mixture of experts (MoE) model in GPT-4. This approach utilizes 16 experts, each consisting of around 111 billion parameters for the <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/multilayer-perceptron-explained-with-a-real-life-example-and-python-code-sentiment-analysis-cb408ee93141">MLP (Multi-Layer Perceptron)</a>. During each forward pass, two experts are routed, simplifying the routing process compared to more advanced algorithms discussed in the literature.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">MoE Routing: A Simpler Approach</h3>



<p>OpenAI&#8217;s routing algorithm for GPT-4 is reportedly straightforward compared to more intricate methods proposed in the research literature. The model employs approximately 55 billion shared parameters for attention, streamlining the routing process.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Inference Efficiency: Optimized Parameter Usage</h3>



<p>One notable aspect of GPT-4 is its impressive inference efficiency. Each forward pass for generating a single token utilizes only around 280 billion parameters and approximately 560 <a href="https://kb.iu.edu/d/apeq#:~:text=for%2031.69%20years.-,TeraFLOPS,every%20second%20for%2031%2C688.77%20years">TFLOPs (tera floating-point operations per second)</a>. This stands in stark contrast to the 1.8 trillion parameters and roughly 3,700 TFLOPs required for a purely dense model per forward pass. The optimized parameter usage contributes to improved performance and reduced computational requirements.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Dataset: Extensive Training Corpus</h3>



<p>GPT-4 is trained on a vast dataset comprising around 13 trillion tokens. It&#8217;s important to note that these tokens include both unique tokens and those generated during multiple epochs. The training process involves two epochs for text-based data and four epochs for code-based data. Additionally, OpenAI incorporated millions of rows of fine-tuning data from ScaleAI and internal sources to enhance the model&#8217;s performance.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">GPT-4 32K: Fine-Tuning the Context Length</h3>



<p>During the pre-training phase, GPT-4 uses an <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/understanding-context-length-hitch-gpt-models-arun-kesavan">8k context length (seqlen)</a>. However, the 32k seqlen version of GPT-4 is achieved through fine-tuning the 8k after the initial pre-training. This approach allows the model to handle longer sequences and capture more extensive context.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Batch Size: Striking a Balance</h3>



<p>OpenAI gradually ramped up the batch size over several days on the cluster, eventually reaching a batch size of 60 million. However, not every expert sees all tokens, resulting in an effective batch size of 7.5 million tokens per expert. The decision to limit the batch size ensures efficient processing and resource utilization.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Parallelism Strategies: Maximizing GPU Utilization</h3>



<p>To parallelize computations across multiple A100 GPUs, OpenAI implemented 8-way tensor parallelism, as this is the maximum supported by <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-in/data-center/nvlink/">NVLink</a>. Furthermore, they adopted 15-way pipeline parallelism to further optimize GPU utilization. It is speculated that OpenAI employed ZeRo Stage 1 and potentially utilized block-level <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2021/07/15/open-source/fsdp/">FSDP (Fully Sharded Data Parallelism) </a>for certain aspects of the training process.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Training Cost: An Expensive Endeavor</h3>



<p>The training of GPT-4 came with substantial costs. OpenAI&#8217;s training FLOPS (floating-point operations per second) for GPT-4 amounted to approximately 2.15e25, utilizing around 25,000 A100 GPUs for 90 to 100 days at a utilization rate of 32% to 36% <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/figure/The-MFU-Cache-Architecture_fig2_2396616">MFU (Memory Frequency Utilization)</a>. Due to numerous failures requiring restarts from checkpoints, the utilization rate remained low. Based on an estimated cloud cost of $1 per A100 hour, the training costs for this run alone would reach approximately $63 million. It is worth noting that pre-training with ~8,192 H100 GPUs could have been done in around 55 days for $21.5 million at a rate of $2 per H100 hour.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Mixture of Expert Tradeoffs: Finding the Right Balance</h3>



<p>OpenAI made specific tradeoffs in implementing the mixture of experts model. While research has shown that using 64 to 128 experts achieves better loss compared to 16 experts, OpenAI chose a more conservative approach. The decision to stick with 16 experts was driven by the challenges associated with generalization across multiple tasks and the difficulty in achieving convergence with a larger number of experts.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">GPT-4 Inference Cost: Scaling with Complexity</h3>



<p>The cost of GPT-4&#8217;s inference is approximately three times higher than that of the 175B parameter GPT-3 model (Davinci). This increased cost primarily stems from the larger clusters required for GPT-4 and the lower utilization achieved during inference. An estimated cost of $0.0049 cents per 1,000 tokens is anticipated for using 128 A100 GPUs to infer GPT-4 with an 8k seqlen. In comparison, the cost reduces to $0.0021 cents per 1,000 tokens when employing 128 H100 GPUs for the same inference task. It should be noted that these estimates assume high utilization and significant batch sizes.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Multi-Query Attention (MQA): Streamlining Processing</h3>



<p>Like many other models, GPT-4 utilizes <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13245">Multi-Query Attention (MQA)</a>. The introduction of MQA reduces the number of attention heads required, leading to a significant reduction in memory capacity for the Key-Value (KV) cache. However, due to the model&#8217;s size, the 32k seqlen GPT-4 cannot run on 40GB A100 GPUs, and the 8k seqlen version has limitations on maximum batch size.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Continuous Batching: Balancing Latency and Inference Costs</h3>



<p>OpenAI has implemented variable batch sizes and continuous batching in GPT-4&#8217;s inference process. This allows for some level of maximum latency while optimizing the overall inference costs. The combination of variable batch sizes and continuous batching ensures efficient resource utilization while maintaining a balance between response times and computational expenses.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Vision Multi-Modal: Enhancing Capabilities</h3>



<p>GPT-4 incorporates a separate vision encoder alongside the text encoder, featuring <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/method/cross-attention-module#:~:text=The%20Cross%2DAttention%20module%20is,are%20projections%20to%20align%20dimensions.">cross-attention</a>. The architecture is similar to Flamingo, adding additional parameters on top of the 1.8 trillion present in GPT-4. The vision model undergoes fine-tuning with an additional ~2 trillion tokens after the initial text-only pre-training. The primary purpose of this vision capability is to enable autonomous agents to read web pages, transcribe content from images and videos, and interact with multi-modal inputs.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Speculative Decoding: Enhancing Inference Efficiency</h3>



<p>There are indications that OpenAI may be employing speculative decoding during GPT-4&#8217;s inference process, although this is not confirmed. Speculative decoding involves using a smaller, faster model to generate several tokens in advance. These tokens are then fed into a larger oracle model as a single batch. If the small model&#8217;s predictions align with the larger model&#8217;s output, several tokens can be decoded in a batch. However, if the larger model rejects the tokens predicted by the smaller model, the rest of the batch is discarded, and the inference continues with the larger model. This approach can optimize efficiency but may impact the quality of generated sequences.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Inference Architecture: Distributed Computing Power</h3>



<p>GPT-4&#8217;s inference is carried out on a cluster comprising 128 GPUs. Multiple clusters are distributed across various data centers in different locations. The model utilizes 8-way tensor parallelism and 16-way pipeline parallelism to effectively leverage the available computational resources. Each node of 8 GPUs handles approximately 130 billion parameters, accommodating the model&#8217;s overall size. The design of the architecture allows for efficient parallel processing and scalability.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Dataset Mixture: A Diverse Training Corpus</h3>



<p>The training process for GPT-4 incorporates a mixture of datasets. The model is trained on approximately 13 trillion tokens, with CommonCrawl and RefinedWeb datasets contributing 5 trillion tokens each. Deduplicating tokens from multiple epochs yields a more reasonable estimate of the &#8220;unaccounted for&#8221; tokens, often referred to as the &#8220;secret&#8221; data. Speculations suggest that parts of this data come from sources such as Twitter, Reddit, YouTube, and platforms like LibGen, Sci-Hub, and GitHub.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">GPT-4&#8217;s Training and Knowledge: A Reflective Illusion</h3>



<p>GPT-4&#8217;s training on an extensive collection of college textbooks, coupled with its ability to answer questions from various domains, creates the illusion of intelligence. This illusion can make it appear knowledgeable in disciplines ranging from computer science to philosophy. Researchers have even attempted to extract memorized parts of books from GPT-4 to better understand its training data. Rumors suggest that the model possesses exceptional familiarity with unique IDs of Project Euler exercises.</p>



<p>In conclusion, GPT-4 represents a significant leap forward in terms of scale, capabilities, and training techniques. Its massive parameter count, mixture of experts model, and efficient inference architecture contribute to its enhanced performance. While the model&#8217;s training process involves a substantial investment, the use of diverse datasets and fine-tuning across multiple domains equips GPT-4 with a broad knowledge base. OpenAI&#8217;s approach to scaling language models demonstrates their commitment to pushing the boundaries of AI research and development.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../gpt-4-details-leaked/index.html">GPT-4: Details Leaked</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../gpt-4-details-leaked/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Day Framework</title>
		<link>./../happy-day-framework/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../happy-day-framework/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:25:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mastering the HappyDay Framework: Unlocking Productivity and Happiness in Entrepreneurship Hey there, fellow entrepreneurs, hustlers, and go-getters! You know that feeling when you wake up in the morning, ready to take on the world, but then find yourself lost in a sea of tasks, decisions, and endless to-dos? Or that moment when you take a&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../happy-day-framework/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Happy Day Framework</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../happy-day-framework/index.html">Happy Day Framework</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h6 class="wp-block-heading">Mastering the HappyDay Framework: Unlocking Productivity and Happiness in Entrepreneurship</h6>



<p>Hey there, fellow entrepreneurs, hustlers, and go-getters! You know that feeling when you wake up in the morning, ready to take on the world, but then find yourself lost in a sea of tasks, decisions, and endless to-dos? Or that moment when you take a step back, analyze your day, and realize that you&#8217;ve been busy doing a million things, but somehow it feels like you&#8217;ve been running in circles. It&#8217;s a gut-wrenching feeling, isn&#8217;t it? </p>



<p>We pour our hearts and souls into our ventures, hustling day in and day out, only to discover that we might have been focusing on the wrong stuff. It&#8217;s frustrating, disheartening even. But here&#8217;s the truth: it happens to the best of us. We get caught up in the whirlwind of tasks and responsibilities, and lose sight of the bigger picture.</p>



<p>So how do we start our day without the chaos and decision fatigue and end our day feeling Happy?</p>



<p>I want to introduce you to the &#8220;HappyDay Framework&#8221; something i try to follow and has worked for me the days I am able to follow it.</p>



<p>HappyDay framework presents a comprehensive set of metrics that captures the key activities and outcomes necessary for success. By monitoring these metrics, startup founders can prioritize their daily tasks and evaluate their productivity. Let&#8217;s delve into the components of the HappyDay framework and understand how they help founders gauge their progress:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Metrics</th><th>Points</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Prospects added to list</td><td>1 point per 10 contacts added</td></tr><tr><td>Conversations with correct contacts</td><td>1 point per conversation</td></tr><tr><td>Value-based emails to Manager+ contacts</td><td>1 point per 5 emails sent</td></tr><tr><td>Initial meetings set</td><td>1 point per meeting</td></tr><tr><td>Opportunities created</td><td>1 point per opportunity</td></tr><tr><td>Personal development</td><td>1 point per hour of development</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Quest for Eight Points: Defining a Productive Day </h3>



<p>The HappyDay framework sets a target of eight points per day, representing a balanced approach that founders can adopt to ensure a productive day focused on sales activities. By aiming for eight points, founders allocate their time effectively across key areas, driving progress and nurturing customer relationships.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A daily checklist</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Main Activities</th><th>Second Level</th><th>Third Level</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Prospecting</td><td>Identify target market segments</td><td>&#8211; Analyze market research reports, industry trends, and customer surveys to identify potential segments.<br>&#8211; Evaluate the size, growth potential, and competitive landscape of each segment.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Utilize advanced search filters or tools on online platforms</td><td>&#8211; Utilize Boolean operators or advanced search options to refine search results.<br>&#8211; Leverage filters such as location, job titles, company size, or industry to target specific leads.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Analyze competitors&#8217; customer base</td><td>&#8211; Research competitors&#8217; websites, social media profiles, or case studies to identify their clients.<br>&#8211; Identify overlaps between competitor clients and your target market to find potential leads.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Keep track of prospecting activities using a CRM system</td><td>&#8211; Use a CRM tool to store and organize prospect information.<br>&#8211; Record interactions, notes, and follow-up tasks within the CRM for easy reference.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Regularly update and maintain the prospecting list</td><td>&#8211; Review and cleanse the prospecting list regularly to remove contacts that are no longer relevant.<br>&#8211; Follow up with unresponsive contacts or update their information if it has changed.</td></tr><tr><td>Conversations</td><td>Prepare a script or talking points</td><td>&#8211; Develop a framework that outlines key talking points, questions, and responses.<br>&#8211; Customize the script for different types of prospects or scenarios.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Practice active listening</td><td>&#8211; Engage in focused listening without interrupting or assuming.<br>&#8211; Ask clarifying questions to ensure a thorough understanding of the prospect&#8217;s challenges.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Take notes during conversations</td><td>&#8211; Use a note-taking tool or CRM system to document key points from each conversation.<br>&#8211; Capture actionable next steps, deadlines, or commitments made during the conversation.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Offer insights, case studies, or success stories</td><td>&#8211; Prepare a repository of relevant industry insights, case studies, or success stories.<br>&#8211; Tailor the examples or stories to resonate with the prospect&#8217;s specific pain points.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Build rapport and establish a relationship</td><td>&#8211; Find common interests or connections to establish a personal connection.<br>&#8211; Remember and reference previous conversations or details to show genuine interest.</td></tr><tr><td>Value-based emails to Manager+ contacts</td><td>Conduct thorough research on each Manager+ contact</td><td>&#8211; Review their LinkedIn profiles, company websites, or press releases for relevant information.<br>&#8211; Seek out news articles, interviews, or blog posts that provide insights into their challenges.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Customize each email</td><td>&#8211; Start with a personalized greeting that acknowledges their position or recent achievements.<br>&#8211; Reference their pain points or specific objectives to demonstrate understanding.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Incorporate relevant data, statistics, or industry trends</td><td>&#8211; Collect and compile data or statistics that highlight industry trends or challenges.<br>&#8211; Use credible sources and provide references or links to support the claims.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Craft compelling subject lines</td><td>&#8211; Use concise, attention-grabbing subject lines that convey value or urgency.<br>&#8211; A/B test subject lines to identify the most effective ones for different target audiences.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>Follow up if there is no response</td><td>&#8211; Set up automated email sequences to follow up at strategic intervals.<br>&#8211; Consider alternative communication channels such as phone calls or LinkedIn messages for follow-ups.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h3>



<p>Startup journey is rewarding and extremely exhausting. It is a marathon and not a sprint. It is about consistency and patience, and doing things even when you don&#8217;t want to. The HappyDay framework I use is to bring structure to this chaos, reduce emotion from the game, and allow one to follow the startup life just like it is tasks that need to get done.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../happy-day-framework/index.html">Happy Day Framework</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../happy-day-framework/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</title>
		<link>./../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 19:16:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=805</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Harnessing the Power of Data Ownership Introduction Language models have revolutionized various aspects of artificial intelligence and natural language processing. With the advancements in technology and the availability of open-source models, many companies are considering the option of developing their own in-house Language Models (LLMs) by fine-tuning existing models on their proprietary data. This approach&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html">The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Harnessing the Power of Data Ownership</p>



<div class="wp-block-ideabox-toc ib-block-toc" data-anchors='h2,h3,h4,h5,h6' data-collapsable='true' ><div class="ib-toc-container ib-toc-list-style-numbers ib-toc-hierarchical ib-toc-expanded"><div class="ib-toc-header"><div class="ib-toc-header-title">Table of Contents</div><div class="ib-toc-header-right"><span class="ib-toc-icon-collapse"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-minus"></span></span><span class="ib-toc-icon-expand"><span class="dashicon dashicons dashicons-plus"></span></span></div></div><div class="ib-toc-separator" style="height:2px"></div><div class="ib-toc-body"><ol class="ib-toc-anchors"></ol></div></div></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Introduction</h3>



<p>Language models have revolutionized various aspects of artificial intelligence and natural language processing. With the advancements in technology and the availability of open-source models, many companies are considering the option of developing their own in-house Language Models (LLMs) by fine-tuning existing models on their proprietary data. This approach offers several advantages and challenges that need to be carefully considered. In this article, we will explore the reasons for and against implementing in-house LLMs and delve into the implications of data ownership in this context.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Enhancing Specialized Tasks:</h3>



<p>One of the primary advantages of fine-tuning an open-source LLM on proprietary data is the potential to improve performance on specialized tasks. A notable example is Microsoft&#8217;s in-house LLM, Turing NLG, which was trained on a diverse range of data, enabling it to generate human-like natural language responses across various applications. This demonstrates the value of in-house LLMs in enhancing specialized tasks that require domain-specific knowledge and industry expertise.</p>



<p>Here is a table that gives some use cases of why in-house LLMs are advantageous:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Use Case</th><th>Description</th><th>Why In-House LLM?</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Legal Research</td><td>Law firms can develop in-house LLMs to analyze and extract relevant information from legal documents, contracts, and case law, improving research efficiency and accuracy.</td><td>In-house LLMs offer greater control over data privacy and confidentiality, ensuring sensitive client information remains within the firm&#8217;s control. Fine-tuning on proprietary legal data enhances accuracy and domain-specific knowledge.</td></tr><tr><td>Financial Analysis</td><td>Financial institutions can leverage in-house LLMs to analyze market data, perform sentiment analysis on news articles, and generate personalized investment recommendations for clients.</td><td>In-house LLMs enable customization and adaptation to specific financial domain requirements, ensuring compliance with industry regulations and providing a competitive advantage through proprietary insights.</td></tr><tr><td>Medical Diagnosis</td><td>Healthcare organizations can develop in-house LLMs to analyze patient medical records, lab reports, and clinical notes, aiding in accurate diagnosis, treatment planning, and patient outcomes.</td><td>In-house LLMs offer the opportunity to train on institution-specific medical data, leading to improved accuracy and tailored insights. Compliance with data protection regulations and maintaining patient privacy can be ensured.</td></tr><tr><td>Customer Support</td><td>Companies with extensive customer support operations can build in-house LLMs to power chatbots or virtual assistants, providing personalized and efficient responses to customer inquiries.</td><td>In-house LLMs allow for better control over the customer support experience, enabling customization, and the ability to address specific industry nuances and jargon. Data privacy concerns can be mitigated, as sensitive customer information remains in-house.</td></tr><tr><td>Content Moderation</td><td>Social media platforms and online communities can develop in-house LLMs to automatically detect and moderate offensive or harmful content, ensuring a safer and more inclusive online environment.</td><td>In-house LLMs provide greater control over content moderation, allowing customization to specific community guidelines, cultural sensitivities, and evolving content trends. Data privacy and security are better maintained within the organization.</td></tr><tr><td>Language Translation</td><td>Organizations with a need for accurate and secure translation services can create in-house LLMs to translate documents, customer communications, and website content, ensuring confidentiality and control over sensitive data.</td><td>In-house LLMs offer the advantage of customization to specific translation requirements, including industry-specific terminology and internal jargon. Data privacy concerns are addressed by keeping translation processes in-house.</td></tr><tr><td>Fraud Detection</td><td>Financial institutions and e-commerce companies can utilize in-house LLMs to detect fraudulent activities by analyzing patterns, anomalies, and transactional data, enhancing security and minimizing losses.</td><td>In-house LLMs enable customization to specific fraud detection needs, incorporating proprietary knowledge and insights. Confidentiality of transactional and customer data can be better safeguarded.</td></tr><tr><td>Sentiment Analysis</td><td>Marketing and market research firms can develop in-house LLMs to analyze social media posts, customer reviews, and survey responses, providing insights into public sentiment towards products or brands.</td><td>In-house LLMs allow for customization to industry-specific sentiment analysis requirements, including specific product features, customer demographics, and sentiment nuances. Proprietary data and insights can be leveraged for a competitive advantage.</td></tr><tr><td>Compliance Monitoring</td><td>Companies operating in highly regulated industries can employ in-house LLMs to monitor and analyze vast amounts of data for compliance with regulatory requirements, reducing risks and ensuring adherence to guidelines.</td><td>In-house LLMs enable customization to specific regulatory frameworks, industry-specific compliance needs, and proprietary data sources. Better control over data privacy and security can be maintained.</td></tr><tr><td>Personalized Recommender Systems</td><td>E-commerce platforms and content streaming services can utilize in-house LLMs</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Data Ownership as a Deciding Factor:</h3>



<p>For many companies, the ownership of data is a critical consideration. Accessing proprietary data through third-party APIs may raise concerns regarding data privacy, security, and confidentiality. Companies like Apple have emphasized data privacy by developing Siri, their voice assistant, with an in-house LLM approach. This ensures that user data remains within the company&#8217;s control, addressing privacy concerns and providing a competitive advantage in the market.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Responsibility for Output and Safety:</h3>



<p>Regardless of whether a company relies on external APIs or in-house LLMs, it remains responsible for the outputs generated by its AI systems. Ethical considerations and potential harm caused by AI outputs are the responsibility of the company utilizing the technology. OpenAI&#8217;s GPT-3, a widely used language model, has shown instances of biased and harmful outputs, emphasizing the importance of thorough checks and balances. By building and fine-tuning their own LLMs, companies can exercise greater control and accountability over the system&#8217;s behavior, ensuring alignment with their desired standards of safety and ethical guidelines.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges and Considerations:</h3>



<p>While the benefits of in-house LLMs are evident, there are several challenges that companies must overcome. Firstly, the legal implications surrounding data usage must be carefully addressed. Different countries have varying &#8220;fair use&#8221; laws, and improper usage of proprietary third-party data can lead to potential lawsuits and legal consequences. For example, Google faced legal challenges in the past regarding the use of copyrighted content in its search results.</p>



<p>Additionally, developing and maintaining in-house LLMs requires a specialized skill set. According to a report by Indeed, the demand for AI-related job roles, including natural language processing experts, has grown by 119% in the past three years. Finding professionals with the necessary expertise in machine learning and deep learning can be a significant challenge for companies.</p>



<p>Furthermore, implementing in-house LLMs can give rise to internal obstacles within a company. These projects often involve complex decision-making processes, internal debates, and political considerations. The necessary approvals and coordination across different departments can cause delays and hinder progress.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Future of In-House LLMs:</h3>



<p>As LLMs continue to evolve and become safer and higher performing out of the box, the adoption of in-house models is expected to accelerate. OpenAI&#8217;s GPT-3, for example, has showcased impressive language generation capabilities. Companies will have more confidence in using these models and fine-tuning them to meet their specific needs. With advancements in cloud computing and the decreasing costs associated with it, hosting and maintaining in-house LLMs will likely become more affordable over time, making it a viable option for an increasing number of organizations.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion:</h3>



<p>The decision to develop and deploy in-house LLMs requires careful consideration of the advantages and challenges involved. Fine-tuning an LLM on proprietary data can lead to improved performance on specialized tasks and greater control over data ownership. However, legal implications, skill requirements, and internal obstacles should be carefully evaluated. As technology progresses, the future of in-house LLMs looks promising, providing companies with the means to harness the full potential of AI while maintaining control and responsibility over their AI systems.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/index.html">The Pros and Cons of In-House Language Models</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../the-pros-and-cons-of-in-house-language-models/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Leading with Purpose: Find Your Ideal Company Type for Impactful Leadership!</title>
		<link>./../leading-with-purpose-find-your-ideal-company-type-for-impactful-leadership/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../leading-with-purpose-find-your-ideal-company-type-for-impactful-leadership/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 08:15:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=798</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This article, inspired by Dr. Sanjiv Kumar&#8217;s course on Public Health Leadership, delves into the intricacies of leadership within different types of organizations. It aims to address a common pain point in today&#8217;s professional landscape: many individuals spend a significant portion of their lives working in jobs that they dislike or find unfulfilling. Surprisingly, only&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../leading-with-purpose-find-your-ideal-company-type-for-impactful-leadership/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Leading with Purpose: Find Your Ideal Company Type for Impactful Leadership!</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../leading-with-purpose-find-your-ideal-company-type-for-impactful-leadership/index.html">Leading with Purpose: Find Your Ideal Company Type for Impactful Leadership!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This article, inspired by <a href="https://www.ihwcouncil.org/profile/dr-sanjiv-kumar/">Dr. Sanjiv Kumar&#8217;s</a> course on <a href="https://mu.linkedin.com/posts/dr-sanjiv-kumar-a5272417_agenda-leadership-course-activity-7050876295391379456-lLGk">Public Health Leadership</a>, delves into the intricacies of leadership within different types of organizations. It aims to address a common pain point in today&#8217;s professional landscape: many individuals spend a significant portion of their lives working in jobs that they dislike or find unfulfilling. Surprisingly, only a fraction of them take the time to perform a personal self-assessment to determine if they are a natural fit for the organization they are working in.</p>



<p>Statistics reveal that job dissatisfaction is pervasive across various industries. According to a <a href="https://haiilo.com/blog/employee-engagement-8-statistics-you-need-to-know/">Gallup survey, a staggering 85% of employees</a> worldwide are disengaged or actively disengaged at work. Another study by the Conference Board found that only 45% of U.S. workers are satisfied with their jobs. These figures highlight the need for individuals to reflect on their own preferences, strengths, and aspirations when considering their career paths.</p>



<p>This article aims to bridge that gap by comparing different organization types and providing a guide to help individuals assess which type may be the best fit for their personality, values, and career goals. By understanding the unique characteristics of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Family_business">family-run companies</a>, <a href="https://corporatefinanceinstitute.com/resources/management/multinational-corporation/">professional large multinational corporations (MNCs)</a>, startups, the military, and government organizations, individuals can gain insights into the leadership styles, structures, and cultures of each type.</p>



<div class="wp-block-table-of-contents-block-table-of-contents-block"><div class="eb-parent-wrapper eb-parent-eb-toc-wa2z0km "><div class="eb-toc-wa2z0km eb-toc-container eb-toc-not-collapsible eb-toc-initially-not-collapsed eb-toc-is-not-sticky eb-toc-not-scrollToTop    " data-scroll-top="false" data-collapsible="false" data-hide-mobile="false" data-sticky="false" data-scroll-target="scroll_to_toc"><div class="eb-toc-header"><div class="eb-toc-title">Table of Contents</div></div><div class="eb-toc-wrapper   " data-headers="[{&quot;level&quot;:4,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Comparative Analysis: Key Criteria for Different Company Types&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Comparative Analysis: Key Criteria for Different Company Types&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;comparative-analysis-key-criteria-for-different-company-types&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:4,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Matching Personality Types with Company Types: A Guide to Finding Your Perfect Fit&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Matching Personality Types with Company Types: A Guide to Finding Your Perfect Fit&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;matching-personality-types-with-company-types-a-guide-to-finding-your-perfect-fit&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:4,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Leadership Styles and their relationship to Organization Types&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Leadership Styles and their relationship to Organization Types&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;leadership-styles-and-their-relationship-to-organization-types&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:4,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Conclusion&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Conclusion&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;conclusion&quot;}]" data-visible="[true,true,true,true,true,true]" data-smooth="true" data-top-offset=""><div class="eb-toc__list-wrap"><ul class="eb-toc__list"><li style="padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#comparative-analysis-key-criteria-for-different-company-types">Comparative Analysis: Key Criteria for Different Company Types</a></li><li style="padding-top:10px;padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#matching-personality-types-with-company-types-a-guide-to-finding-your-perfect-fit">Matching Personality Types with Company Types: A Guide to Finding Your Perfect Fit</a></li><li style="padding-top:10px;padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#leadership-styles-and-their-relationship-to-organization-types">Leadership Styles and their relationship to Organization Types</a></li><li style="padding-top:10px;padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li></ul></div></div></div></div></div>



<p>The intention is not to prescribe a one-size-fits-all solution, but rather to empower individuals to make informed decisions about their professional journeys. By undertaking a personal self-assessment and considering the attributes of different organization types, individuals can better align their skills, aspirations, and work preferences with their chosen organizational environment.</p>



<p>Through the comparison of organization types and the provision of a self-assessment guide, this article aims to assist individuals in identifying the organization type that best suits their personality and professional goals. By addressing the pain point of job dissatisfaction and encouraging self-reflection, we hope to guide individuals towards a more fulfilling and harmonious career path, where they can thrive and make a meaningful impact.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Comparative Analysis: Key Criteria for Different Company Types</h4>



<p>In this section, we present a comparative analysis of different company types based on key criteria, offering insights into their distinctive characteristics and leadership dynamics. Understanding the similarities and differences among family-run &#8220;lala&#8221; companies, professional large multinational corporations (MNCs), startups, the military, and government organizations can help individuals gain a comprehensive understanding of each type&#8217;s work environment, growth opportunities, communication styles, and conflict resolution approaches.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Criteria</th><th>Family-Run &#8220;Lala&#8221; Company</th><th>Professional Large MNC</th><th>Startup</th><th>Army</th><th>Government</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Organizational Structure</td><td>Informal and flexible</td><td>Formal and hierarchical</td><td>Agile and fluid</td><td>Hierarchical and structured</td><td>Bureaucratic and hierarchical</td></tr><tr><td>Decision-making</td><td>Often centralized with family members making key decisions</td><td>Decentralized, involving multiple stakeholders and committees</td><td>Collaborative, involving a small team of founders</td><td>Top-down, with clear chains of command</td><td>Decentralized with decision-making processes involving multiple levels</td></tr><tr><td>Conflict Resolution</td><td>Informal and personal, often resolved through mediation or family intervention</td><td>Formal processes, involving HR and conflict resolution teams</td><td>Open and direct communication, addressing conflicts proactively</td><td>Hierarchical resolution, following established protocols</td><td>Mediation, negotiation, and legal procedures depending on the nature and scale of conflicts</td></tr><tr><td>Consensus Building</td><td>Influenced by family dynamics and personal relationships</td><td>Collaboration and consensus-seeking among diverse stakeholders</td><td>Transparent decision-making, involving team members in the process</td><td>Consensus through clear orders and directives</td><td>Political negotiations and consensus-building processes involving multiple stakeholders</td></tr><tr><td>Communication</td><td>Informal and often face-to-face</td><td>Formal, structured, and multi-channel</td><td>Open, direct, and frequent</td><td>Clear and concise, following established protocols</td><td>Formal and structured, often involving paperwork and documentation</td></tr><tr><td>Risk-Tolerance</td><td>Conservative and cautious</td><td>Balanced, considering risk and reward</td><td>High risk appetite, embracing uncertainty</td><td>Moderate risk appetite, focused on minimizing casualties</td><td>Varies depending on specific government policies and priorities</td></tr><tr><td>Innovation and Adaptability</td><td>Slow to adopt change and innovation</td><td>Embraces innovation and adapts to market trends</td><td>Nimble and agile, encourages experimentation</td><td>Adapts quickly to evolving situations</td><td>Varies depending on government policies and regulations</td></tr><tr><td>Resource Allocation</td><td>Limited resources, potential reliance on personal connections</td><td>Efficient allocation based on budgets and performance</td><td>Flexible allocation, prioritizing growth opportunities</td><td>Rigorous planning and allocation based on mission objectives</td><td>Governed by budgetary constraints and allocation processes</td></tr><tr><td>Leadership Style</td><td>Personal and relationship-based, with strong influence of family members</td><td>Professional and strategic, balancing employee needs with organizational goals</td><td>Entrepreneurial, empowering and inspiring team members</td><td>Authoritative and disciplined, focused on mission accomplishment</td><td>Politically astute, balancing public interest and policy implementation</td></tr><tr><td>Employee Motivation</td><td>Often based on loyalty, family ties, and job security</td><td>Recognition, career growth, and competitive compensation</td><td>Shared vision, autonomy, and potential equity ownership</td><td>Discipline, sense of duty, and mission focus</td><td>Public service, sense of duty, and impact on society</td></tr><tr><td>Performance Evaluation</td><td>Informal and subjective, often based on personal relationships</td><td>Formal and objective, based on clear performance metrics</td><td>Flexible and adaptive, focused on milestones and agility</td><td>Structured, based on predefined criteria and standards</td><td>Governed by performance indicators and evaluation processes</td></tr><tr><td>Stakeholder Management</td><td>Family members and long-term relationships</td><td>Diverse stakeholders, including shareholders, customers, and employees</td><td>Early adopters, investors, and potential partners</td><td>Collaborative, including superiors, peers, and subordinates</td><td>Public constituents, interest groups, and intergovernmental relationships</td></tr><tr><td>External Perception</td><td>Perceived as traditional and local</td><td>Established and trustworthy</td><td>Perceived as innovative and disruptive</td><td>Respected and disciplined</td><td>Perceived as authoritative and representative of public interest</td></tr><tr><td>Succession Planning</td><td>Family lineage and inheritance</td><td>Talent-driven and merit-based</td><td>Adaptable to business needs and growth</td><td>Based on rank and experience</td><td>Regulated by political processes and appointments</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Matching Personality Types with Company Types: A Guide to Finding Your Perfect Fit</h4>



<p>In order to thrive and excel in their professional lives, individuals need to find an organizational environment that complements their personality traits, work preferences, and values. Understanding the relationship between personality types and different company types can be instrumental in identifying the ideal organizational fit. In this section, we present a guide that correlates various personality types with different company types, providing valuable insights into the compatibility between individuals and their work environments. By assessing their own personalities and considering the characteristics of each company type, individuals can make informed decisions that maximize their potential for success, job satisfaction, and long-term fulfillment.</p>



<p>Here&#8217;s a table that helps individuals assess which company or organization type might be best for them based on their personality type:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Personality Type</th><th>Family-Run Company</th><th>Professional Large MNC</th><th>Startup</th><th>Army</th><th>Government</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Independent and entrepreneurial</td><td>Limited decision-making autonomy</td><td>Potential for limited creativity and innovation</td><td>High level of autonomy and freedom to experiment</td><td>Moderate level of autonomy, depending on rank</td><td>Moderate level of autonomy, depending on role</td></tr><tr><td>Collaborative and team-oriented</td><td>Strong sense of belonging and family-like environment</td><td>Opportunities for cross-functional collaboration</td><td>Emphasis on teamwork and collective efforts</td><td>Strong sense of camaraderie and teamwork</td><td>Opportunities for collaboration with diverse stakeholders</td></tr><tr><td>Risk-tolerant and adaptive</td><td>Limited exposure to risk and slower adaptation to change</td><td>Opportunities for calculated risk-taking and adaptability</td><td>High risk-reward ratio and willingness to embrace uncertainty</td><td>Moderate level of risk-taking, focused on mission objectives</td><td>Moderate level of risk-taking, dependent on specific government policies</td></tr><tr><td>Result-driven and competitive</td><td>Potential limitations in attracting and retaining top talent</td><td>Opportunities for career growth and recognition</td><td>Opportunities for rapid growth and potential for equity ownership</td><td>Focus on performance and mission accomplishment</td><td>Opportunities for impact and influence on public policies</td></tr><tr><td>Stability and job security</td><td>Potential reliance on personal relationships and job security</td><td>Stable and established work environment</td><td>Potential for high growth and reward, but with higher uncertainty</td><td>Job security and stable career progression</td><td>Potential for job security and stability</td></tr><tr><td>Creativity and innovation</td><td>Potential limitations in adopting change and innovation</td><td>Opportunities for innovation within established processes</td><td>Opportunities for disruptive thinking and innovation</td><td>Limited scope for individual innovation, but opportunity for teamwork</td><td>Potential for innovation in policy development and public service</td></tr><tr><td>Work-life balance and flexibility</td><td>Potential flexibility in work arrangements</td><td>Varied work-life balance based on job role</td><td>Potential for flexible work arrangements and autonomy</td><td>Structured work-life balance and routines</td><td>Structured work-life balance and adherence to protocols</td></tr><tr><td>Leadership and decision-making</td><td>Potential influence of family members in decision-making</td><td>Opportunities for leadership roles based on merit and performance</td><td>Opportunities for entrepreneurial leadership and decision-making</td><td>Clear hierarchical leadership structure</td><td>Opportunities for leadership in public service and policy-making</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>table that includes a scoring mechanism where individuals can multiply their self-assigned scores for each personality type by the corresponding scores for each organization type. They can then sum up the multiplied scores to find the organization type with the highest total score:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Personality Type</th><th>Family-Run Company</th><th>Professional Large MNC</th><th>Startup</th><th>Army</th><th>Government</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Independent and entrepreneurial</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Collaborative and team-oriented</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Risk-tolerant and adaptive</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Result-driven and competitive</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Stability and job security</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Creativity and innovation</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>3</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Work-life balance and flexibility</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>3</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Leadership and decision-making</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>5</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>To determine the best organizational fit, follow these steps:</p>



<ol>
<li>Score yourself on each personality type based on your own preferences and characteristics, ranging from 1 (low fit) to 5 (high fit).</li>



<li>Multiply your self-assigned scores for each personality type by the corresponding scores for each organization type.</li>



<li>Sum up the multiplied scores for each organization type.</li>



<li>The organization type with the highest total score is likely to be the best fit for you based on your personality traits and preferences.</li>
</ol>



<p>For example, if you scored yourself 4 for &#8220;Independent and entrepreneurial&#8221; personality type, you would multiply it by the corresponding scores for each organization type (Family-Run &#8220;Lala&#8221; Company: 2, Professional Large MNC: 3, Startup: 4, Army: 3, Government: 2). Repeat this process for each personality type and organization type, and then sum up the multiplied scores to find the highest total score.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Leadership Styles and their relationship to Organization Types</h4>



<p>It is also important to asses which leadership style is a great fit for which company type. First, it can help you asses that the company you are a part of is under the right leadership, and second you can asses if you can rise to the right level of leadership based on your personal preference</p>



<ol>
<li>Autocratic: Autocratic leaders make decisions independently and enforce them without much input from others. They have centralized authority and control over the decision-making process, often resulting in a top-down approach. This style can be effective in situations that require quick decision-making or in highly structured environments like the military.</li>



<li>Democratic: Democratic leaders involve team members in the decision-making process, seeking their input and considering their perspectives. They encourage collaboration, participation, and open communication. This style promotes a sense of ownership among team members and fosters a positive work environment.</li>



<li>Laissez-Faire: Laissez-faire leaders adopt a hands-off approach, allowing employees to make decisions and work independently with minimal supervision. They provide freedom and autonomy to their team members, trusting them to take ownership of their tasks and make their own choices. This style can be effective in creative and innovative environments, such as startups.</li>



<li>Transformational: Transformational leaders inspire and motivate their teams through a compelling vision and a focus on personal development. They encourage creativity, challenge the status quo, and empower individuals to reach their full potential. This style fosters a positive and high-performance work culture.</li>



<li>Transactional: Transactional leaders focus on setting clear expectations, providing rewards, and enforcing consequences based on performance. They establish a clear framework of tasks, goals, and rewards, emphasizing the exchange between leaders and followers. This style is often seen in professional MNCs with well-defined hierarchies.</li>



<li>Servant: Servant leaders prioritize the needs and growth of their team members. They serve others by supporting their development, providing guidance, and removing obstacles. This style promotes a sense of collaboration, empathy, and a focus on the well-being of employees.</li>



<li>Charismatic: Charismatic leaders possess strong personal charisma and influence. They inspire and motivate others through their compelling vision, persuasive communication, and magnetic personality. This style can be influential in startups or organizations with a strong emphasis on entrepreneurship.</li>



<li>Situational/Adaptive: Situational or adaptive leaders are flexible and adjust their leadership style based on the needs of the situation and the capabilities of their team members. They assess the situation, consider the strengths and weaknesses of their team, and adapt their approach accordingly to maximize effectiveness.</li>
</ol>



<p>Remember that leadership styles are not mutually exclusive, and effective leaders often blend multiple styles based on the context and the individuals they lead. The key is to be adaptable and employ the most appropriate style for the given circumstances and organizational culture.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th>Leadership Style</th><th>Family-Run &#8220;Lala&#8221; Company</th><th>Professional Large MNC</th><th>Startup</th><th>Army</th><th>Government</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Autocratic</td><td>High</td><td>Low</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td><td>Medium</td></tr><tr><td>Democratic</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td></tr><tr><td>Laissez-Faire</td><td>Low</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td><td>Low</td><td>Low</td></tr><tr><td>Transformational</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>Medium</td></tr><tr><td>Transactional</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td><td>Medium</td></tr><tr><td>Servant</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>High</td></tr><tr><td>Charismatic</td><td>Low</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>High</td></tr><tr><td>Situational/Adaptive</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>High</td><td>Medium</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>Note: The table above provides a general perspective on which leadership styles tend to suit different company types. However, it&#8217;s important to remember that leadership styles can vary even within the same company type, and there can be exceptions to the general tendencies mentioned here. Additionally, effective leadership requires a combination of various styles, adaptability, and alignment with the organization&#8217;s values, culture, and goals.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h4>



<p>As we conclude, it is important to acknowledge that leadership is a continuous learning process. Dr. Kumar&#8217;s course has imparted valuable leadership lessons, emphasizing the importance of adaptability, effective communication, and the ability to inspire and motivate others. These lessons transcend organizational boundaries and can be applied in any leadership role.</p>



<p>Finding the right organizational fit is vital for long-term job satisfaction and personal fulfillment. By exploring different company types and their characteristics, we have provided insights into leadership styles, work environments, communication styles, and conflict resolution approaches. Our guide and scoring mechanism offer a practical tool for individuals to assess their compatibility with various company types based on their personality traits.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../leading-with-purpose-find-your-ideal-company-type-for-impactful-leadership/index.html">Leading with Purpose: Find Your Ideal Company Type for Impactful Leadership!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../leading-with-purpose-find-your-ideal-company-type-for-impactful-leadership/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brand Building on a Budget: How Startups Beat the Big Guns</title>
		<link>./../brand-building-on-a-budget-how-startups-beat-the-big-guns/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../brand-building-on-a-budget-how-startups-beat-the-big-guns/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 15:09:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=792</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Inspired by an insightful talk delivered by Amit Jain, Chairman &#38; MD India, L&#8217;Oreal, at the CODE summit in Delhi, I felt compelled to share the strategies and secrets that enable startups to achieve remarkable branding success despite limited resources. In a world dominated by renowned brands like Coca-Cola, Nike, and L&#8217;Oreal, startups and indie&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../brand-building-on-a-budget-how-startups-beat-the-big-guns/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">Brand Building on a Budget: How Startups Beat the Big Guns</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../brand-building-on-a-budget-how-startups-beat-the-big-guns/index.html">Brand Building on a Budget: How Startups Beat the Big Guns</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Inspired by an insightful talk delivered by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/amit-jain-1591752/?original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fcode.exmyb.com%2F">Amit Jain, Chairman &amp; MD India, L&#8217;Oreal</a>, at the <a href="https://code.exmyb.com/">CODE summit</a> in Delhi, I felt compelled to share the strategies and secrets that enable startups to achieve remarkable branding success despite limited resources. In a world dominated by renowned brands like Coca-Cola, Nike, and L&#8217;Oreal, startups and indie hackers often find themselves facing a significant challenge: how to achieve a strong brand presence with limited budgets and resources. However, with the right approach and innovative strategies, these underdogs can still make a significant impact. In this article, we will explore how startups can leverage emotional differentiation and cultural differentiation to establish their brands and connect with their target audience, ultimately leading to long-term success.</p>



<div class="wp-block-table-of-contents-block-table-of-contents-block alignfull"><div class="eb-parent-wrapper eb-parent-eb-toc-zdkyome "><div class="eb-toc-zdkyome eb-toc-container eb-toc-not-collapsible eb-toc-initially-not-collapsed eb-toc-is-not-sticky eb-toc-not-scrollToTop    " data-scroll-top="false" data-collapsible="false" data-hide-mobile="false" data-sticky="false" data-scroll-target="scroll_to_toc"><div class="eb-toc-header"><div class="eb-toc-title">Table of Contents</div></div><div class="eb-toc-wrapper   " data-headers="[{&quot;level&quot;:4,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Emotional Differentiation: Connecting on a Deeper Level:&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Emotional Differentiation: Connecting on a Deeper Level:&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;emotional-differentiation-connecting-on-a-deeper-level&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:5,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;a) Authentic Brand Storytelling: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;a) Authentic Brand Storytelling: &quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;a-authentic-brand-storytelling&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:6,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;How can your startup do Authentic Brand Storytelling?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;How can your startup do Authentic Brand Storytelling?&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;how-can-your-startup-do-authentic-brand-storytelling&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:5,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;b) Empathetic Customer Understanding: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;b) Empathetic Customer Understanding: &quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;b-empathetic-customer-understanding&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:6,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;How can your startup do Empathetic Customer Understanding?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;How can your startup do Empathetic Customer Understanding?&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;how-can-your-startup-do-empathetic-customer-understanding&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:5,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;c) Personalized Customer Experiences: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;c) Personalized Customer Experiences: &quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;c-personalized-customer-experiences&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:6,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;How can you startup do Personalized Customer Experiences?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;How can you startup do Personalized Customer Experiences?&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;how-can-you-startup-do-personalized-customer-experiences&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:4,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Cultural Differentiation: Establishing a Unique Brand Identity:&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Cultural Differentiation: Establishing a Unique Brand Identity:&quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;cultural-differentiation-establishing-a-unique-brand-identity&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:5,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;a) Niche Marketing: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;a) Niche Marketing: &quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;a-niche-marketing&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:5,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;b) Collaborations and Partnerships: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;b) Collaborations and Partnerships: &quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;b-collaborations-and-partnerships&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:5,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;c) Localization and Cultural Adaptation: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;c) Localization and Cultural Adaptation: &quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;c-localization-and-cultural-adaptation&quot;},{&quot;level&quot;:4,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Conclusion: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Conclusion: &quot;,&quot;link&quot;:&quot;conclusion&quot;}]" data-visible="[true,true,true,true,true,true]" data-smooth="true" data-top-offset=""><div class="eb-toc__list-wrap"><ul class="eb-toc__list"><li style="padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#emotional-differentiation-connecting-on-a-deeper-level">Emotional Differentiation: Connecting on a Deeper Level:</a></li><ul class="eb-toc__list"><li style="padding-top:10px;padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#a-authentic-brand-storytelling">a) Authentic Brand Storytelling: </a></li><ul class="eb-toc__list"><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#how-can-your-startup-do-authentic-brand-storytelling">How can your startup do Authentic Brand Storytelling?</a></li></ul><li style="padding-top:10px;padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#b-empathetic-customer-understanding">b) Empathetic Customer Understanding: </a></li><ul class="eb-toc__list"><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#how-can-your-startup-do-empathetic-customer-understanding">How can your startup do Empathetic Customer Understanding?</a></li></ul><li style="padding-top:10px;padding-bottom:10px"><a href="#c-personalized-customer-experiences">c) Personalized Customer Experiences: </a></li><ul class="eb-toc__list"><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#how-can-you-startup-do-personalized-customer-experiences">How can you startup do Personalized Customer Experiences?</a></li></ul></ul><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#cultural-differentiation-establishing-a-unique-brand-identity">Cultural Differentiation: Establishing a Unique Brand Identity:</a></li><ul class="eb-toc__list"><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#a-niche-marketing">a) Niche Marketing: </a></li><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#b-collaborations-and-partnerships">b) Collaborations and Partnerships: </a></li><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#c-localization-and-cultural-adaptation">c) Localization and Cultural Adaptation: </a></li></ul><li style="padding-top:10px"><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion: </a></li></ul></div></div></div></div></div>



<p></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Emotional Differentiation: Connecting on a Deeper Level:</h4>



<p>One of the most powerful tools in a startup&#8217;s branding arsenal is emotional differentiation. While larger companies may have extensive budgets to create emotional connections, startups can achieve similar results through strategic storytelling, empathy, and authenticity. Here&#8217;s how they can do it:</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">a) Authentic Brand Storytelling: </h5>



<p>Startups can craft compelling narratives around their brand, focusing on their mission, values, and the problem they aim to solve. By sharing relatable stories and experiences, startups can create an emotional bond with their audience, driving loyalty and trust.</p>



<p>Example: Warby Parker, an online eyewear retailer, differentiated itself by sharing the story of its founders&#8217; frustration with the high cost of glasses. Their narrative emphasized affordable yet stylish eyewear, resonating with customers who were tired of overpriced options. This authentic brand story helped Warby Parker gain a dedicated following and disrupt the traditional eyewear industry.</p>



<h6 class="wp-block-heading">How can your startup do Authentic Brand Storytelling?</h6>



<p>Step 1: Identify your mission and values: Start by defining the purpose and core values of your startup. Understand the problem you aim to solve and the impact you want to make in your customers&#8217; lives.</p>



<p>Step 2: Discover your unique story: Reflect on the journey that led to the creation of your startup. Uncover the personal experiences, challenges, or insights that inspired your venture. Find the narrative that resonates with your target audience.</p>



<p>Step 3: Craft compelling messaging: Develop a brand story that communicates your mission, values, and unique selling proposition. Connect emotionally with your audience by highlighting how your startup addresses their needs and aspirations.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">b) Empathetic Customer Understanding: </h5>



<p>By actively listening and empathizing with their customers, startups can gain valuable insights into their needs, desires, and pain points. This understanding allows them to tailor their messaging and product offerings to resonate with their target audience on an emotional level.</p>



<p>Example: Airbnb built a strong emotional connection with its customers by focusing on the concept of belonging. Through their &#8220;Belong Anywhere&#8221; campaign, Airbnb showcased heartwarming stories of travelers and hosts coming together, highlighting the emotional value of their platform beyond mere accommodations. This approach created a sense of community and trust, setting them apart from traditional hotel chains.</p>



<h6 class="wp-block-heading">How can your startup do Empathetic Customer Understanding?</h6>



<p>Step 1: Conduct customer research: Engage with your target audience through surveys, interviews, or social media interactions. Seek to understand their pain points, desires, and motivations. Identify common themes and emotions associated with their experiences.</p>



<p>Step 2: Analyze customer feedback and data: Dive deep into customer feedback, reviews, and usage data. Look for patterns and insights that can help you understand the emotional aspects that drive their connection to your product or service.</p>



<p>Step 3: Tailor your messaging and product experience: Use the insights gained to refine your brand messaging and align it with the emotional needs and aspirations of your customers. Personalize your product experience to deliver moments that evoke positive emotions and create a lasting impact.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">c) Personalized Customer Experiences: </h5>



<p>Startups can create memorable and personalized experiences for their customers. By going the extra mile to show appreciation and deliver exceptional customer service, they can forge strong emotional connections that differentiate them from larger, impersonal corporations.</p>



<p>Example: Stitch Fix, an online personal styling service, uses data-driven algorithms and human stylists to create personalized clothing recommendations for each customer. By tailoring their offerings to individual preferences, Stitch Fix delivers a unique and personalized experience, generating a sense of loyalty and emotional connection.</p>



<h6 class="wp-block-heading">How can you startup do Personalized Customer Experiences?</h6>



<p>Step 1: Develop a customer-centric approach: Put your customers at the center of your business strategy. Build systems and processes that prioritize exceptional customer service and create opportunities for personalization.</p>



<p>Step 2: Implement CRM tools and data analysis: Utilize customer relationship management (CRM) tools to gather and analyze data about your customers&#8217; preferences, purchase history, and interactions. Leverage this information to tailor your offerings and communications.</p>



<p>Step 3: Surprise and delight your customers: Go beyond expectations by offering personalized recommendations, exclusive deals, or handwritten notes. Show genuine appreciation for their support and foster a sense of connection that sets you apart from larger, impersonal corporations.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Cultural Differentiation: Establishing a Unique Brand Identity:</h4>



<p>Cultural differentiation plays a vital role in helping startups establish their brands and stand out in a crowded marketplace. Startups can tap into cultural nuances and values to resonate with their target audience. Here are some ways startups can leverage cultural differentiation:</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">a) Niche Marketing: </h5>



<p>Startups can focus on specific niche markets that align with their values, beliefs, and interests. By tailoring their brand messaging, products, and marketing efforts to cater to these niche segments, startups can position themselves as the go-to solution for a particular cultural community.</p>



<p>Example: Glossier, a skincare and beauty brand, gained a cult following by targeting a niche audience of millennials seeking a more natural and minimalist approach to beauty. Their inclusive brand messaging, minimalist packaging, and focus on skincare over heavy makeup helped them stand out in a crowded market, establishing Glossier as a cultural phenomenon.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">b) Collaborations and Partnerships: </h5>



<p>Startups can build alliances with influencers, content creators, or other brands that share their cultural values. These partnerships can help amplify their reach, build credibility, and create a unique brand identity that resonates with their target audience.</p>



<p>Example: Fenty Beauty, founded by Rihanna, disrupted the beauty industry by emphasizing inclusivity and diversity. Through collaborations with influencers and celebrities from various backgrounds, Fenty Beauty showcased a wide range of products suitable for different skin tones, setting a new standard for inclusivity in the beauty industry.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">c) Localization and Cultural Adaptation: </h5>



<p>Startups can adapt their products, services, and marketing strategies to the cultural nuances of different regions. By understanding the local customs, language, and preferences, startups can create a deeper connection with their target audience, establishing their brand as one that understands and respects local culture.</p>



<p>Example: Spotify localized its platform to cater to diverse music cultures worldwide. By curating playlists and featuring local artists, Spotify established a strong connection with users in different countries, showcasing an understanding and appreciation for their unique musical preferences and cultural identities.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion: </h4>



<p>Although startups and indie hackers may lack the financial resources and brand recognition of giant corporations, they possess unique advantages when it comes to branding. By leveraging emotional differentiation and cultural differentiation, startups can connect with their customers on a deeper level and establish a brand that resonates with their target audience. Through examples like Warby Parker, Airbnb, Glossier, and Spotify, we see that strategic storytelling, empathy, authenticity, cultural alignment, and personalized experiences can help startups achieve remarkable branding successes, laying the foundation for long-term growth and success.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../brand-building-on-a-budget-how-startups-beat-the-big-guns/index.html">Brand Building on a Budget: How Startups Beat the Big Guns</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../brand-building-on-a-budget-how-startups-beat-the-big-guns/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to come with a startup idea if you are bootstrapping or an indie hacker</title>
		<link>./../how-to-come-with-a-startup-idea-if-you-are-bootstrapping-or-an-indie-hacker/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../how-to-come-with-a-startup-idea-if-you-are-bootstrapping-or-an-indie-hacker/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rohitkumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 20:27:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=569</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>There are a few different ways to come up with startup ideas: 1. Look at what’s already out there and find a way to improve it 2. Solve a problem that you or someone you know is experiencing This is the common advice. The problem I find is that this approach gives you too many&#8230;&#160;<a href="./../how-to-come-with-a-startup-idea-if-you-are-bootstrapping-or-an-indie-hacker/index.html" class="" rel="bookmark">Read More &#187;<span class="screen-reader-text">How to come with a startup idea if you are bootstrapping or an indie hacker</span></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../how-to-come-with-a-startup-idea-if-you-are-bootstrapping-or-an-indie-hacker/index.html">How to come with a startup idea if you are bootstrapping or an indie hacker</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>There are a few different ways to come up with startup ideas:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/how_to_turn_your_start_up_ideas_into_a_business.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-570" width="817" height="457" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/how_to_turn_your_start_up_ideas_into_a_business.jpg 408w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/how_to_turn_your_start_up_ideas_into_a_business-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 817px) 100vw, 817px" /></figure>



<p>1. Look at what’s already out there and find a way to improve it</p>



<p>2. Solve a problem that you or someone you know is experiencing</p>



<p>This is the common advice. The problem I find is that this approach gives you too many ideas.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">So how can you find ideas that you have passion for?</h2>



<p>So one secret to finding ideas that you have a passion for is to focus on things that you do daily.</p>



<p>For example, If you spend a lot of time say in investment just observe, what are the things that you feel like doing and you’re not able to do? What do you spend more time doing?</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/aid1557372-v4-1200px-Sharpen-Your-Powers-of-Observation-Step-13-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-571" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/aid1557372-v4-1200px-Sharpen-Your-Powers-of-Observation-Step-13-1024x768.jpg 1024w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/aid1557372-v4-1200px-Sharpen-Your-Powers-of-Observation-Step-13-300x225.jpg 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/aid1557372-v4-1200px-Sharpen-Your-Powers-of-Observation-Step-13-768x576.jpg 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/aid1557372-v4-1200px-Sharpen-Your-Powers-of-Observation-Step-13.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Let’s say, for example, you’re spending a lot of time or effort in figuring out comparing a stock or reading the transcript report, just observe, figure out what while reading the transcript, what are you trying to get out of it and see if you can fundamentally come up or use a disruptive technology to to eliminate that.</p>



<p>See, there is always a market so you want to look at current market for a product like this would be that somebody would pay for. In this case, let’s say a financial analyst is going through these talks and identifying what exactly is the transcript earning calls transcript is saying, What if you could develop technology that could do the same? What if it is not just technology, what if you could, connect people to other people who can potentially help you accomplish this and make them do things for each other so that it’s gets the same job done.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Summary</h2>



<p>To conclude, a quick tip, when the day ends, or maybe the start of the day, just simply write all your observations.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="780" height="439" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/stephanie-rimando-metro-vancouver-journal-writer.webp" alt="" class="wp-image-572" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/stephanie-rimando-metro-vancouver-journal-writer.webp 780w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/stephanie-rimando-metro-vancouver-journal-writer-300x169.webp 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/stephanie-rimando-metro-vancouver-journal-writer-768x432.webp 768w" sizes="(max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /></figure>



<p>Write what you saw, what you spent more time on, resist the temptation to get ideas or judge your observations. Resist the temptation to come up the solution to the problem, Just take note of the emotion. Notice what is happening. Soon you will discover a theme emerging, an opportunity will emerge.</p>



<p>Good news is that this opportunity will be something you have passion towards. In my next blog I will cover what other things to ensure when you are evaluating this opportunity, so stay tuned.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../how-to-come-with-a-startup-idea-if-you-are-bootstrapping-or-an-indie-hacker/index.html">How to come with a startup idea if you are bootstrapping or an indie hacker</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../index.html">PlainSwipe</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../how-to-come-with-a-startup-idea-if-you-are-bootstrapping-or-an-indie-hacker/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
